<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-changing-functions-spherical-tank-draining">

	<statement>
		<p>
			Consider a spherical tank of radius <m>4</m> m that is completely full of water.  Suppose that the tank is being drained by regulating an exit valve in such a way that the height of the water in the tank is always decreasing at a rate of <m>0.5</m> meters per minute.  Let 
			<m>V</m> be the volume of water in the tank (in cubic meters) at a given time <m>t</m> (in minutes), and
			<m>h</m> the depth of the water (in meters) at the same time.  It can be shown using calculus 
			that <m>V</m> is a function of <m>t</m> according to the model
      		<me>
        		V = p(t) = \frac{256\pi}{3} - \frac{\pi}{24} t^2(24-t)
      		</me>.
      		In addition, let <m>h = q(t)</m> be the function whose output is the depth of the water in the tank at time <m>t</m>. 
		</p>

		<p>
			<ol marker="a.">
				<li>
					<p>
						What is the height of the water when <m>t = 0</m>?  When <m>t = 1</m>? When <m>t = 2</m>?  How long will it take the tank to completely drain?  Why?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						What is the domain of the model <m>h = q(t)</m>?  What is the domain of the model <m>V = p(t)</m>?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						How much water is in the tank when the tank is full?  What is the range of the model <m>h = q(t)</m>?  What is the range of the model <m>V = p(t)</m>?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						We will frequently use a graphing utility to help us understand function behavior, and strongly recommend <url href="https://www.desmos.com/"><em>Desmos</em></url> because it is intuitive, online, and free.<fn>To learn more about <em>Desmos</em>, see their <url href="http://learn.desmos.com/">outstanding online tutorials</url>.</fn>
					</p>

					<p>
						In <url href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/btlyyxsdr4">this prepared <em>Desmos</em> worksheet</url>, you can see how we enter the (abstract) function <m>V = p(t) = \frac{256\pi}{3} - \frac{\pi}{24} t^2(24-t)</m>, as well as the corresponding graph the program generates.  Make as many observations as you can about the model <m>V = p(t)</m>.  You should discuss its shape and overall behavior, its domain, its range, and more. 
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
			            How does the model <m>V = p(t) = \frac{256\pi}{3} - \frac{\pi}{24} t^2(24-t)</m> differ from the abstract function <m>y = r(x) = \frac{256\pi}{3} - \frac{\pi}{24} x^2(24-x)</m>?  In particular, how do the domain and range of the model differ from those of the abstract function, if at all?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						How should the graph of the height function <m>h = q(t)</m> appear?  Can you determine a formula for <m>q</m>?  Explain your thinking.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</p>
	</statement>
	<answer>
		<p>
			
		</p>
	</answer>
	<solution>
		<p>
			
		</p>
	</solution>

</activity>

