<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-tandem-spherical-tank">

	<statement>
		<p>
			Consider a tank in the shape of a sphere where the tank's radius is <m>3</m> feet.  Suppose that the tank is initially completely full and that it is being drained by a pump at a constant rate of <m>1.2</m> cubic feet per minute.
		</p>

		<p>
			<ol marker="a.">
				<li>
					<p>
						Sketch a labeled picture of the tank, including a snapshot of some water remaining in the tank prior to the tank being completely empty.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						What are some quantities that are changing in this scenario?  What are some quantities that are not changing?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Recall that the volume of a sphere of radius <m>r</m> is <m>V = \frac{4}{3} \pi r^3</m>.  When the tank is completely full at time <m>t = 0</m> right before it starts being drained, how much water is present?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						How long will it take for the tank to drain completely?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Fill in the following table of values to determine how much water, <m>V</m>, is in the tank at a given time in minutes, <m>t</m>, and thus generate a graph of the relationship between volume and time.  Write a sentence to explain why the data's graph appears the way that it does.
					</p>
					<sidebyside width="50%" valign="middle">
						<table xml:id="T-tandem-act-sphere-V-t">
							<caption>Data for how volume and time change together.</caption>
							<tabular>
								<row bottom="minor">
									<cell><m>t</m></cell>
									<cell><m>V</m></cell>
								</row>
								<row>
									<cell><m>0</m></cell>
									<cell></cell>
								</row>
								<row>
									<cell><m>20</m></cell>
									<cell></cell>
								</row>
								<row>
									<cell><m>40</m></cell>
									<cell></cell>
								</row>
								<row>
									<cell><m>60</m></cell>
									<cell></cell>
								</row>
								<row>
									<cell><m>80</m></cell>
									<cell></cell>
								</row>																	
								<row>
									<cell><m>94.24</m></cell>
									<cell></cell>
								</row>															
							</tabular>
						</table>
						<figure xml:id="F-tandem-act-sphere-V-t">
							<caption>A plot of how volume and time change in tandem in a draining spherical tank.</caption>
							<image source="images/tandem-sphere-V-t" />	
						</figure>
					</sidebyside>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Finally, think about how the height of the water changes in tandem with time. What is the height of the water when <m>t = 0</m>?  What is the height when the tank is empty?  How would you expect the data for the relationship between <m>h</m> and <m>t</m> to appear?  Use the provided axes to sketch at least two possibilities; write at least one sentence to explain how you think the graph should appear.
					</p>
					<sidebyside width="50%">
			              <image source="images/tandem-h-t-blank-axes" /> <image source="images/tandem-h-t-blank-axes" />
					</sidebyside>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</p>
	</statement>
	<answer>
		<p>
			
		</p>
	</answer>
	<solution>
		<p>
			
		</p>
	</solution>

</activity>