<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-changing-tandem">

<!-- THIS ONE WORKS -->
  <exercise xml:id="ez-changing-tandem-WW0" label="Library__LoyolaChicago__Precalc__Chap1Review__Q37">
    <webwork source="Library/LoyolaChicago/Precalc/Chap1Review/Q37.pg"/>
  </exercise>


<!-- doesn't render in PDF bc no statement tag
  <exercise xml:id="ez-changing-tandem-WW1" label="Library__Rochester__setAlgebra16FunctionGraphs__c0s1p8__c0s1p8">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setAlgebra16FunctionGraphs/c0s1p8/c0s1p8.pg" />
  </exercise>
-->

  <exercise xml:id="ez-tandem-spherical-tank-conical-chimney">
    <statement>
      <p>
        Suppose we have an unusual tank whose base is a perfect sphere with radius <m>3</m> feet, and then atop the spherical base is a cylindrical <q>chimney</q> that is a circular cylinder of radius <m>1</m> foot and height <m>2</m> feet, as shown in <xref ref="F-ez-chiminea">Figure</xref>.  The tank is initially empty, but then a spigot is turned on that pumps water into the tank at a constant rate of <m>1.25</m> cubic feet per minute.
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-ez-chiminea">
        <caption>A spherical tank with a cylindrical chimney.</caption>
        <image width="50%" source="images/tandem-ez-chiminea"><description><p>A spherical tank with a cylindrical chimney.</p>
        </description></image>   
      </figure>

      <p>
        Let <m>V</m> denote the total volume of water (in cubic feet) in the tank at any time <m>t</m> (in minutes), and <m>h</m> the depth of the water (in feet) at time <m>t</m>.
      </p> 
  
      <p>
        <ol marker="a.">
          <li>
            <p>
              It is possible to use calculus to show that the total volume this tank can hold is <m>V_{\text{full}} = \pi(20 + \frac{38}{3}\sqrt{2}) \approx 119.11</m> cubic feet.  In addition, the actual height of the tank (from the bottom of the spherical base to the top of the chimney) is <m>h_{\text{full}} = \sqrt{8} + 5 \approx 7.83</m> feet.  How long does it take the tank to fill?   Why?
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              On the blank axes provided below, sketch (by hand) possible graphs of how <m>V</m> and <m>t</m> change in tandem and how <m>h</m> and <m>t</m> change in tandem.
            </p>

            <sidebyside width="50%">
              <image source="images/tandem-V-t-blank-axes"><description><p>ADD ALT TEXT TO THIS IMAGE</p></description></image>
              <image source="images/tandem-h-t-blank-axes"><description><p>ADD ALT TEXT TO THIS IMAGE</p></description></image>
            </sidebyside>

            <p>
              For each graph, label any ordered pairs on the graph that you know for certain, and write at least one sentence that explains why your graphs have the shape they do.
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              How would your graph(s) change (if at all) if the chimney was shaped like an inverted cone instead of a cylinder?  Explain and discuss.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>

    </statement>
    <answer>
      <p>
        Exercise Answer
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution>
      <p><ol marker="a."><li><p>At a fill rate of <m>1.25</m> cu ft/min, the time to fill is <m>\frac{V_{\text{full}}}{1.25} = \frac{\pi(20 + \frac{38}{3}\sqrt{2})}{1.25} \approx \frac{119.11}{1.25} \approx 95.3</m> minutes.</p></li><li><p>The graph of <m>V</m> vs <m>t</m> is a straight line with slope <m>1.25</m> from <m>(0,0)</m> to <m>(95.3, 119.11)</m>. The graph of <m>h</m> vs <m>t</m> is an S-shaped increasing curve: initially <m>h</m> rises quickly as the narrow bottom of the sphere fills, then more slowly as the widest part of the sphere fills, then speeds up slightly as the narrow chimney fills. Key points include <m>(0,0)</m>, the time when <m>h = \sqrt{8} + 3 \approx 5.83</m> ft (sphere full, chimney starts), and the endpoint <m>(95.3, \sqrt{8}+5)</m>.</p></li><li><p>If the chimney were an inverted cone, its cross-section would shrink as it fills, so the height would increase more quickly in the chimney. The <m>V</m>-vs-<m>t</m> graph would not change (still linear), but the <m>h</m>-vs-<m>t</m> graph would rise more steeply once the water enters the cone-shaped chimney.</p></li></ol></p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-tandem-spherical-tank-height-constant-rate">
    <statement>
      <p>
        Suppose we have a tank that is a perfect sphere with radius <m>6</m> feet.  The tank is initially empty, but then a spigot is turned on that is pumping water into the tank in a very special way:  the faucet is regulated so that the depth of water in the tank is increasing at a constant rate of <m>0.4</m> feet per minute.
      </p>

      <p>
        Let <m>V</m> denote the total volume of water (in cubic feet) in the tank at any time <m>t</m> (in minutes), and <m>h</m> the depth of the water (in feet) at given time <m>t</m>.
      </p> 
  
      <p>
        <ol marker="a.">
          <li>
            <p>
              How long does it take the tank to fill?  What will the values of <m>V</m> and <m>h</m> be at the moment the tank is full?  Why?
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              On the blank axes provided below, sketch (by hand) possible graphs of how <m>V</m> and <m>t</m> change in tandem and how <m>h</m> and <m>t</m> change in tandem.
            </p>

            <sidebyside width="50%">
              <image source="images/tandem-V-t-blank-axes"><description><p>ADD ALT TEXT TO THIS IMAGE</p></description></image>
              <image source="images/tandem-h-t-blank-axes"><description><p>ADD ALT TEXT TO THIS IMAGE</p></description></image>
            </sidebyside>

            <p>
              For each graph, label any ordered pairs on the graph that you know for certain, and write at least one sentence that explains why your graphs have the shape they do.
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              How do your responses change if the tank stays the same but instead the tank is initially full and the tank drains in such a way that the height of the water is always decreasing at a constant rate of <m>0.25</m> feet per minute?
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>

    </statement>
    <answer>
      <p>
        Exercise Answer
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution>
      <p><ol marker="a."><li><p>At a constant rate of <m>0.4</m> ft/min, the depth reaches <m>12</m> ft (the diameter) in <m>12/0.4 = 30</m> minutes. At that time, <m>V = \frac{4}{3}\pi(6)^3 = 288\pi \approx 904.8</m> cu ft.</p></li><li><p>Since the height rises linearly, <m>h = 0.4t</m> is a straight line. The volume <m>V</m> as a function of <m>t</m> starts slowly (the bottom of the sphere is narrow), increases rapidly through the middle (widest part of sphere), and slows again as the top narrows. The <m>V</m>-vs-<m>t</m> graph is S-shaped (concave up then concave down). Key points: <m>(0,0)</m> and <m>(30, 288\pi)</m>.</p></li><li><p>For the draining scenario: <m>h</m> starts at <m>12</m> ft and decreases linearly at <m>0.25</m> ft/min to <m>0</m> in <m>48</m> minutes. The <m>h</m>-vs-<m>t</m> graph is a decreasing line. The <m>V</m>-vs-<m>t</m> graph is an S-shaped decreasing curve (symmetric to the filling case), from <m>(0, 288\pi)</m> to <m>(48, 0)</m>.</p></li></ol></p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-tandem-car-position-time">
    <statement>
      <p>
        The relationship between the position, <m>s</m>, of a car driving on a straight road at time <m>t</m> is given by the graph
        pictured at left in <xref ref="F-tandem-car-pos">Figure</xref>.
        The car's position<fn>You can think of the car's position like mile-markers on a highway.  Saying that <m>s = 500</m> means that the car is located <m>500</m> feet from <q>marker zero</q> on the road.</fn> has units measured in thousands of feet while time is measured in minutes.
        For instance, the point <m>(4,6)</m> on the graph indicates that after <m>4</m> minutes,
        the car has traveled <m>6000</m> feet from its starting location.
      </p>

      <p>
        <ol marker="a.">
          <li>
            <p>
              Write several sentences that explain the how the car is being driven and how you make these conclusions from the graph.
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              How far did the car travel between <m>t = 2</m> and <m>t = 10</m>?
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              Does the car ever travel in reverse?  Why or why not?  If not, how would the graph have to look to indicate such motion?
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              On the blank axes in <xref ref="F-tandem-car-pos">Figure</xref>, plot points or sketch a curve to describe the behavior of a car that is driven in the following way:  from <m>t = 0</m> to <m>t = 5</m> the car travels straight down the road at a constant rate of <m>1000</m> feet per minute.  At <m>t = 5</m>, the car pulls over and parks for <m>2</m> full minutes.  Then, at <m>t = 7</m>, the car does an abrupt U-turn and returns in the opposite direction at a constant rate of <m>800</m> feet per minute for <m>5</m> additional minutes.  As part of your work, determine (and label) the car's location at several additional points in time other than <m>t = 0, 5, 7, 12</m>.
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="F-tandem-car-pos">
                <caption>A graph of the relationship between a car's position <m>s</m> and time <m>t</m></caption>
        <sidebyside width="50%">
          <image source="images/tandem-ez-position-time"><description><p>A graph of the relationship between a car's position <m>s</m> and time <m>t</m></p>
        </description></image>
          <image source="images/tandem-ez-position-time-blank-axes"><description><p>A graph of the relationship between a car's position <m>s</m> and time <m>t</m></p>
        </description></image>
        </sidebyside>
            </figure>

          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
      
    </statement>
    <answer>
      <p>
        Exercise Answer
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution>
      <p><ol marker="a."><li><p>Describe the car based on the graph: on intervals where <m>s</m> is increasing, the car moves forward; where <m>s</m> is flat, the car is stopped; where <m>s</m> decreases, the car is in reverse. The slope (steepness) indicates speed.</p></li><li><p>From the graph, <m>s(2)</m> and <m>s(10)</m> can be read. The distance traveled between <m>t = 2</m> and <m>t = 10</m> is <m>|s(10) - s(2)|</m> thousand feet.</p></li><li><p>If the position graph is always non-decreasing (never moves backward), the car never goes in reverse. A graph that decreases (negative slope) over some interval would indicate reverse motion.</p></li><li><p>For the described motion: <m>t = 0</m>: <m>s = 0</m>. At <m>t = 5</m>: <m>s = 1000 \times 5 = 5000</m> ft (i.e., <m>5</m> thousand ft). From <m>t = 5</m> to <m>t = 7</m>: car is stopped, so <m>s = 5</m>. At <m>t = 7</m>: U-turn, moving at <m>-800</m> ft/min. At <m>t = 12</m>: <m>s = 5000 - 800 \times 5 = 5000 - 4000 = 1000</m> ft (i.e., <m>1</m> thousand ft). Plot a line of slope <m>1</m> from <m>(0,0)</m> to <m>(5,5)</m>, horizontal from <m>(5,5)</m> to <m>(7,5)</m>, and a line of slope <m>-0.8</m> from <m>(7,5)</m> to <m>(12,1)</m>.</p></li></ol></p>
    </solution>    
  </exercise>

</exercises>
