<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<exploration xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="PA-circular-traversing">

	<statement>
		<p>
			In the context of the ferris wheel pictured in <xref ref="F-traversing-ferris-wheel-animation">Figure</xref>, assume that the height, <m>h</m>, of the moving point (the cab in which you are riding), and the distance, <m>d</m>, that the point has traveled around the circumference of the ferris wheel are both measured in meters.  
		</p>
			
		<p>	
			Further, assume that the circumference of the ferris wheel is <m>150</m> meters.  In addition, suppose that after getting in your cab at the lowest point on the wheel, you traverse the full circle several times.
		</p>

		<p>
			<ol marker="a.">
				<li>
					<p>
						Recall that the circumference, <m>C</m>, of a circle is connected to the circle's radius, <m>r</m>, by the formula <m>C = 2\pi r</m>.  What is the radius of the ferris wheel?  How high is the highest point on the ferris wheel?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						How high is the cab after it has traveled <m>1/4</m> of the circumference of the circle?  
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						How much distance along the circle has the cab traversed at the moment it first reaches a height of <m>\frac{150}{\pi} \approx 47.75</m> meters?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Can <m>h</m> be thought of as a function of <m>d</m>?  Why or why not?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Can <m>d</m> be thought of as a function of <m>h</m>?  Why or why not?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Why do you think the curve shown at right in <xref ref="F-traversing-ferris-wheel-animation">Figure</xref> has the shape that it does?  Write several sentences to explain.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</p>
	</statement>

</exploration>