<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<exploration xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="PA-poly-polynomials">

	<statement>
		<p>
			Point your browser to the <em>Desmos</em> worksheet at <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/0zy">http://gvsu.edu/s/0zy</url>.  There you'll find a degree <m>4</m> polynomial of the form <m>p(x) = a_0 + a_1x + a_2x^2 + a_3x^3 + a_4x^4</m>, where <m>a_0, \ldots, a_4</m> are set up as sliders.  In the questions that follow, you'll experiment with different values of <m>a_0, \ldots, a_4</m> to investigate different possible behaviors in a degree <m>4</m> polynomial.
		</p>

		<p>
			<ol marker="a.">
				<li>
					<p>
						What is the largest number of distinct points at which <m>p(x)</m> can cross the <m>x</m>-axis? 
					</p>

					<p>
						For a polynomial <m>p</m>, we call any value <m>r</m> such that <m>p(r) = 0</m> a <term>zero</term> of the polynomial.  <idx><h>polynomial function</h><h>zero</h></idx> Report the values of <m>a_0, \ldots, a_4</m> that lead to that largest number of zeros for <m>p(x)</m>.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						What other numbers of zeros are possible for <m>p(x)</m>?  Said differently, can you get each possible number of fewer zeros than the largest number that you found in (a)? Why or why not?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						We say that a function has a <term>turning point</term> <idx><h>turning point</h></idx> if the function changes from decreasing to increasing or increasing to decreasing at the point.  For example, any quadratic function has a turning point at its vertex.
					</p>

					<p>
						What is the largest number of turning points that <m>p(x)</m> (the function in the <em>Desmos</em> worksheet) can have?  Experiment with the sliders, and report values of <m>a_0, \ldots, a_4</m> that lead to that largest number of turning points for <m>p(x)</m>.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						What other numbers of turning points are possible for <m>p(x)</m>? Can it have no turning points?  Just one?  Exactly two? Experiment and explain.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						What long-range behavior is possible for <m>p(x)</m>?  Said differently, what are the possible results for <m>\displaystyle \lim_{x \to -\infty} p(x)</m> and <m>\displaystyle \lim_{x \to \infty} p(x)</m>?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						What happens when we plot <m>y = a_4 x^4</m> in and compare <m>p(x)</m> and <m>a_4 x^4</m>?  How do they look when we zoom out? (Experiment with different values of each of the sliders, too.)
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</p>
	</statement>

</exploration>