<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2018                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Preparation for Calculus.                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-0-0-0">
  
<!--
  <exercise xml:id="ez-0-0-WW1">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap2Sec1/Q17.pg" />
  </exercise>
  <exercise xml:id="ez-0-0-WW2">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap2Sec1/Q17.pg" />
  </exercise>
-->

  <exercise xml:id="ez-trig-tangent-ramp">
    <statement>
      <p>
        A wheelchair ramp is to be built so that the angle it forms with level ground is <m>4^{\circ}</m>.
        If the ramp is going to rise from a level sidewalk up to a front porch that is <m>3</m> feet above the ground,
        how long does the ramp have to be?
        How far from the front porch will it meet the sidewalk?
        What is the slope of the ramp?
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer>
      <p>
        Exercise Answer
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution>
      <p>
        Exercise Solution
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-trig-tangent-kite">
    <statement>
      <p>
        A person is flying a kite and at the end of a fixed length of string.  Assume there is no slack in the string.
      </p>

      <p>
        At a certain moment, the kite is <m>170</m> feet off the ground, and the angle of elevation the string makes with the ground is <m>40^\circ</m>.
      </p>

      <p>
        <ol label="a.">
          <li>
            <p>
              How far is it from the person flying the kite to another person who is standing directly beneath the kite?
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              How much string is out between the person flying the kite and the kite itself?
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              With the same amount of string out, the angle of elevation increases to <m>50^\circ</m>.  How high is the kite at this time?
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer>
      <p>
        Exercise Answer
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution>
      <p>
        Exercise Solution
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-trig-tangent-plane">
    <statement>
      <p>
        An airplane is flying at a constant speed along a straight path above a straight road at a constant elevation of <m>2400</m> feet.  A person on the road observes the plane flying directly at them and uses a sextant to measure the angle of elevation from them to the plane.  The first measurement they take records an angle of <m>36^\circ</m>; a second measurement taken <m>2</m> seconds later is <m>41^\circ</m>.
      </p>

      <p>
        How far did the plane travel during the two seconds between the two angle measurements?  How fast was the plane flying?
      </p>
    </statement>
    <answer>
      <p>
        Exercise Answer
      </p>
    </answer>
    <solution>
      <p>
        Exercise Solution
      </p>
    </solution>
  </exercise>

</exercises>
