<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2018                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Preparation for Calculus.                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-circular-sinusoidal">
  <title>Sinusoidal Functions</title>
  <objectives>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How do the three standard transformations (vertical translation, horizontal translation, and vertical scaling) affect the midline, amplitude, range, and period of sine and cosine curves?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				What algebraic transformation results in horizontal stretching or scaling of a function?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How can we determine a formula involving sine or cosine that models any circular periodic function for which the midline, amplitude, period, and an anchor point are known?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>
  </objectives>
  <introduction>
  	<p>
  		Recall our work in <xref ref="sec-changing-transformations">Section</xref>, where we studied how the graph of the function <m>g</m> defined by <m>g(x) = af(x-b) + c</m> is related to the graph of <m>f</m>, where <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> are real numbers with <m>a \ne 0</m>.  Because such transformations can shift and stretch a function, we are interested in understanding how we can use transformations of the sine and cosine functions to fit formulas to circular functions.
  	</p>

  	<xi:include href="./previews/PA-circular-sinusoidal.xml" />

  </introduction>
  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-sinusoidal-shifts-stretches">
  	<title>Shifts and vertical stretches of the sine and cosine functions</title>
  	<p>
  		We know that the standard functions <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m> and <m>g(t) = \cos(t)</m> are circular functions that each have midline <m>y = 0</m>, amplitude <m>a = 1</m>, period <m>p = 2\pi</m>, and range <m>[-1,1]</m>.  Our work in <xref ref="PA-circular-sinusoidal">Preview Activity</xref> suggests the following general principles.
  	</p>

  	<assemblage xml:id="asm-sinusoidal-first-transformations">
  		<title>Transformations of sine and cosine</title>
  		<p>
  			Given real numbers <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> with <m>a \ne 0</m>, the functions
  			<me>
  				k(t) = a\cos(t-b)+c \text{ and } h(t) = a\sin(t-b) + c
  			</me>
  			each represent a horizontal shift by <m>b</m> units to the right, followed by a vertical stretch by <m>a</m> units, followed by a vertical shift of <m>c</m> units, applied to the parent function (<m>\cos(t)</m> or <m>\sin(t)</m>, respectively).  The resulting circular functions have midline <m>y = c</m>, amplitude <m>a</m>, range <m>[c-a,c+a]</m>, and period <m>p = 2\pi</m>.  In addition, the point <m>(b,a+c)</m> lies on the graph of <m>k</m> and the point <m>(b,c)</m> lies on the graph of <m>h</m>.
  		</p>
  	</assemblage>

  	<p>
  		In <xref ref="F-sinusoidal-cosine-transf">Figure</xref>, we see how the overall transformation <m>k(t) = a\cos(t-b)+c</m> comes from executing a sequence of simpler ones.  The original parent function <m>y = \cos(t)</m> (in dark gray) is first shifted <m>b</m> units right to generate the light red graph of <m>y = \cos(t - b)</m>.  In turn, that graph is then scaled vertically by <m>a</m> to generate the purple graph of <m>y = a\cos(t-b)</m>.  Finally, the purple graph is shifted <m>c</m> units vertically to result in the final graph of <m>y = a\cos(t-b) + c</m> in blue.
  	</p>

  	<figure xml:id="F-sinusoidal-cosine-transf">
  		<caption>A sequence of transformations of <m>y = \cos(t)</m>.</caption>
  		<image width="80%" source="images/sinusoidal-transformed-cosine" />
  	</figure>

  	<p>
  		It is often useful to follow one particular point through a sequence of transformations.  In <xref ref="F-sinusoidal-cosine-transf">Figure</xref>, we see the red point that is located at <m>(0,1)</m> on the original function <m>y = \cos(t)</m>, as well as the point <m>(b, a+c)</m> that is the corresponding point on <m>k(t) = a\cos(t-b) + c</m> under the overall transformation.  Note that the point <m>(b,a+c)</m> results from the input, <m>t = b</m>, that makes the argument of the cosine function zero:  <m>k(b) = a\cos(b-b) + c = a\cos(0) + c</m>.  
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		While the sine and cosine functions extend infinitely in either direction, it's natural to think of the point <m>(0,1)</m> as the <q>starting point</q> of the cosine function, and similarly the point <m>(0,0)</m> as the starting point of the sine function.  We will refer to the corresponding points <m>(b,a+c)</m> and <m>(b,c)</m> on <m>k(t) = a\cos(t-b) + c</m> and <m>h(t) = a\sin(t-b) + c</m> as <term>anchor points</term>. <idx><h>sinusoidal function</h><h>anchor point</h></idx>  Anchor points, along with other information about a circular function's amplitude, midline, and period help us to determine a formula for a function that fits a given situation.
  	</p>

  	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-sinusoidal-oscillator.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-sinusoidal-horiz-scaling">
  	<title>Horizontal scaling</title>

	<p>
		There is one more very important transformation of a function that we've not yet explored.  Given a function <m>y = f(x)</m>, we want to understand the related function <m>g(x) = f(kx)</m>, where <m>k</m> is a positive real number.  The sine and cosine functions are ideal functions with which to explore these effects; moreover, this transformation is crucial for being able to use the sine and cosine functions to model phenomena that oscillate at different frequencies.
	</p>

	<p>
		In the interactive <xref ref="F-transformations-horizontal-scaling">Figure</xref>,  we can explore the effect of the transformation <m>g(t) = f(kt)</m>, where <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m>.
	</p>

	<figure xml:id="F-transformations-horizontal-scaling">
		<caption>Interactive horizontal scaling demonstration (in the HTML version only).</caption>

		<interactive xml:id="I-transformations-horizontal-scaling" platform="javascript" width="75%" aspect="4:5" source = "interactives/figures.js interactives/transformationsC.js" preview="images/transformations-interactive-C-static.jpg">
			<slate xml:id="cslider" aspect="4:1" surface="canvas" />
			<slate xml:id="compressing" aspect="4:4" surface="canvas" />
			<instructions>
				<p>
					Move the slider by clicking and dragging on the red point to see how changing <m>k</m> affects the graph of <m>y = f(kt)</m>.  The graph of <m>y = f(t)</m> will appear in grey and remain fixed. 
				</p>
			</instructions>
		</interactive>
	</figure> 

	<p>
		By experimenting with the slider, we gain an intuitive sense for how the value of <m>k</m> affects the graph of <m>h(t) = f(kt)</m> in comparision to the graph of <m>f(t)</m>.  When <m>k = 2</m>, we see that the graph of <m>h</m> is oscillating twice as fast as the graph of <m>f</m> since <m>h(t) = f(2t)</m> completes two full cycles over an interval in which <m>f</m> completes one full cycle.  In contrast, when <m>k = \frac{1}{2}</m>, the graph of <m>h</m> oscillates half as fast as the graph of <m>f</m>, as <m>h(t) = f(\frac{1}{2}t)</m> completes only half of one cycle over an interval where <m>f(t)</m> completes a full one.
	</p>

	<p>
		We can also understand this from the perspective of function composition.  To evaluate <m>h(t) = f(2t)</m>, at a given value of <m>t</m>, we first multiply the input <m>t</m> by a factor of <m>2</m>, and then evaluate the function <m>f</m> at the result.  An important observation is that 
		<me>
			h\left( \frac{1}{2}t \right) = f\left( 2 \cdot \frac{1}{2}t \right) = f(t)
		</me>.
		This tells us that the point <m>(\frac{1}{2}t, f(t))</m> lies on the graph of <m>h</m> since an input of <m>\frac{1}{2}t</m> in <m>h</m> results in the value <m>f(t)</m>.  At the same time, the point <m>(t,f(t))</m> lies on the graph of <m>f</m>.  Thus we see that the correlation between points on the graphs of <m>f</m> and <m>h</m> (where <m>h(t) = f(2t)</m>) is
		<me>
			(t, f(t)) \rightarrow \left( \frac{1}{2}t, f(t) \right)
		</me>.
		We can therefore think of the transformation <m>h(t) = f(2t)</m> as achieving the output values of <m>f</m> twice as fast as the original function <m>f(t)</m> does.  Analogously, the transformation <m>h(t) = f(\frac{1}{2}t)</m> will achieve the output values of <m>f</m> only half as quickly as the original function.
	</p>

  	<assemblage xref="asm-transformations-horizontal-stretch">
  		<title>Horizontal scaling</title>
  		<idx><h>horizontal scaling</h></idx>
  		<p>
  			Given a function <m>y = f(t)</m> and a real number <m>k \gt 0</m>, the transformed function <m>y = h(t) = f(kt)</m> is a <em>horizontal stretch</em> of the graph of <m>f</m>.  Every point <m>(t,f(t))</m> on the graph of <m>f</m> gets stretched horizontally to the corresponding point <m>(\frac{1}{k}t,f(t))</m> on the graph of <m>h</m>.  If <m>0 \lt k \lt 1</m>, the graph of <m>v</m> is a stretch of <m>f</m> away from the <m>y</m>-axis by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{k}</m>; if <m>k \gt 1</m>, the graph of <m>h</m> is a compression of <m>f</m> toward the <m>y</m>-axis by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{k}</m>.  The only point on the graph of <m>f</m> that is unchanged by the transformation is <m>(0,f(0))</m>.
  		</p>
  	</assemblage>

  	<p>
  		While we will soon focus on horizontal stretches of the sine and cosine functions for the remainder of this section, it's important to note that horizontal scaling follows the same principles for any function we choose.
  	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-sinusoidal-horiz-stretch.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
  	<title>Circular functions with different periods</title>
  	<p>
  		Because the circumference of the unit circle is <m>2\pi</m>, the sine and cosine functions each have period <m>2\pi</m>.  Of course, as we think about using transformations of the sine and cosine functions to model different phenomena, it is apparent that we will need to generate functions with different periods than <m>2\pi</m>.  For instance, if a ferris wheel makes one revolution every <m>5</m> minutes, we'd want the period of the function that models the height of one car as a function of time to be <m>P = 5</m>.  Horizontal scaling of functions enables us to generate circular functions with any period we desire.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		We begin by considering two basic examples.  First, let <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m> and <m>g(t) = f(2t) = \sin(2t)</m>.  We know from our most recent work that this transformation results in a horizontal compression of the graph of <m>\sin(t)</m> by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> toward the <m>y</m>-axis.  If we plot the two functions on the same axes as seen in <xref ref="F-sinusoidal-sine-compressed">Figure</xref>, it becomes apparent how this transformation affects the period of <m>f</m>.
  	</p>

  	<figure xml:id="F-sinusoidal-sine-compressed">
  		<caption>A plot of the parent function, <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m> (dashed, in gray), and the transformed function <m>g(t) = f(2t) = \sin(2t)</m> (in blue).</caption>
  		<image source="images/sinusoidal-sine-horiz-scaling" />
  	</figure>

  	<p>
  		From the graph, we see that <m>g(t) = \sin(2t)</m> oscillates twice as frequently as <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m>, and that <m>g</m> completes a full cycle on the interval <m>[0,\pi]</m>, which is half the length of the period of <m>f</m>.  Thus, the  <q><m>2</m></q> in <m>f(2t)</m> causes the period of <m>f</m> to be <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> as long; specifially, the period of <m>g</m> is <m>P = \frac{1}{2} (2\pi) = \pi</m>.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		On the other hand, if we let <m>h(t) = f(\frac{1}{2}t) = \sin(\frac{1}{2}t)</m>, the transformed graph <m>h</m> is stretched away from the <m>y</m>-axis by a factor of <m>2</m>.  This has the effect of doubling the period of <m>f</m>, so that the period of <m>h</m> is <m>P = 2 \cdot 2\pi = 4\pi</m>, as seen in <xref ref="F-sinusoidal-sine-stretched">Figure</xref>.
  	</p>

  	<figure xml:id="F-sinusoidal-sine-stretched">
  		<caption>A plot of the parent function, <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m> (dashed, in gray), and the transformed function <m>h(t) = f(\frac{1}{2}t) = \sin(\frac{1}{2}t)</m> (in blue).</caption>
  		<image source="images/sinusoidal-sine-horiz-scaling-2" />
  	</figure>

  <p>
  	Our observations generalize for any positive constant <m>k \gt 0</m>.  In the case where <m>k = 2</m>, we saw that the period of <m>g(t) = \sin(2t)</m> is <m>P = \frac{1}{2} \cdot 2\pi</m>, whereas in the case where <m>k = \frac{1}{2}</m>, the period of <m>h(t) = \sin(\frac{1}{2}t)</m> is <m>P = 2 \cdot 2\pi = \frac{1}{\frac{1}{2}} \cdot 2\pi</m>.  Identical reasoning holds if we are instead working with the cosine function.  In general, we can say the following.
  </p>

  <assemblage xml:id="asm-sinusoidal-period">
  	<title>The period of a circular function</title>
  	<p>
  		For any constant <m>k \gt 0</m>, the period of the functions <m>\sin(kt)</m> and <m>\cos(kt)</m> is
  		<me>
  			P = \frac{2\pi}{k}
  		</me>.
  	</p>
  </assemblage>

	<p>
		Thus, if we know the <m>k</m>-value from the given function, we can deduce the period.  If instead we know the desired period, we can determine <m>k</m> by the rule <m>k = \frac{2\pi}{P}</m>.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-sinusoidal-period.xml" />

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-sinusoidal-model.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-sinusoidal-summary">
  	<title>Summary</title>

	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Given real numbers <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> with <m>a \ne 0</m>, the functions
	  			<me>
	  				k(t) = a\cos(t-b)+c \text{ and } h(t) = a\sin(t-b) + c
	  			</me>
	  			each represent a horizontal shift by <m>b</m> units to the right, followed by a vertical stretch by <m>a</m> units, followed by a vertical shift of <m>c</m> units, applied to the parent function (<m>\cos(t)</m> or <m>\sin(t)</m>, respectively).  The resulting circular functions have midline <m>y = c</m>, amplitude <m>a</m>, range <m>[c-a,c+a]</m>, and period <m>p = 2\pi</m>.  In addition, the anchor point <m>(b,a+c)</m> lies on the graph of <m>k</m> and the anchor point <m>(b,c)</m> lies on the graph of <m>h</m>.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Given a function <m>f</m> and a constant <m>k \gt 0</m>, the algebraic transformation <m>h(t) = f(kt)</m> results in horizontal scaling of <m>f</m> by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{k}</m>.  In particular, when <m>k \gt 1</m>, the graph of <m>f</m> is compressed toward the <m>y</m>-axis by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{k}</m> to create the graph of <m>h</m>, while when <m>0 \lt k \lt 1</m>, the graph of <m>f</m> is stretched away from the <m>y</m>-axis by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{k}</m> to create the graph of <m>h</m>.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Given any circular periodic function for which the midline, amplitude, period, and an anchor point are known, we can find a corresponding formula for the function of the form 
  				<me>
  					k(t) = a\cos(k(t-b))+c \text{ or } h(t) = a\sin(k(t-b)) + c
  				</me>.
  				Each of these functions has period midline <m>y = c</m>, amplitude <m>a</m>, and period <m>P = \frac{2\pi}{k}</m>.  The point <m>(b,a+c)</m> lies on <m>k</m> and the point <m>(b,c)</m> lies on <m>h</m>.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>

  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-circular-sinusoidal.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->
</section>

