<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2018                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Preparation for Calculus.                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-changing-composite">
  <title>Composite Functions</title>

  <objectives>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How does the process of function composition produce a new function from two other functions?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				In the composite function <m>h(x) = f(g(x))</m>, what do we mean by the <q>inner</q> and <q>outer</q> function?  What role do the domain and codomain of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> play in determining the domain and codomain of <m>h</m>?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How does the expression for <m>AV_{[a,a+h]}</m> involve a composite function?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction>
	<p>
		Recall that a function, by definition, is a process that takes a collection of inputs and produces a corresponding collection of outputs in such a way that the process produces one and only one output value for any single input value.  Because every function is a process, it makes sense to think that it may be possible to take two function processes and do one of the processes first, and then apply the second process to the result.
	</p>

	<example xml:id="ex-composite-introduction">
		<statement>
			<p>
				Suppose we know that <m>y</m> is a function of <m>x</m> according to the process defined by <m>y = f(x) = x^2 - 1</m> and, in turn, <m>x</m> is a function of <m>t</m> via <m>x = g(t) = 3t-4</m>.  Is it possible to combine these processes to generate a new function so that <m>y</m> is a function of <m>t</m>?
			</p>
		</statement>
		<solution>
			<p>
				Since <m>y</m> depends on <m>x</m> and <m>x</m> depends on <m>t</m>, it follows that we can also think of <m>y</m> depending directly on <m>t</m>.  We can use substitution and the notation of functions to determine this relationship.
			</p>

			<p>
				First, it's important to realize what the rule for <m>f</m> tells us.  In words, <m>f</m> says <q>to generate the output that corresponds to an input, take the input and square it, and then subtract <m>1</m>.</q>  In symbols, we might express <m>f</m> more generally by writing <q><m>f(\Box) = \Box^2 - 1</m>.</q>
			</p>

			<p>
				Now, observing that <m>y = f(x) = x^2 - 1</m> and that <m>x = g(t) = 3t - 4</m>, we can substitute the expression <m>g(t)</m> for <m>x</m> in <m>f</m>.  Doing so,
				<md>
					<mrow>y &amp;= f(x)</mrow>
					<mrow>  &amp;= f(g(t))</mrow>
					<mrow>  &amp;= f(3t-4)</mrow>
				</md>.
				Applying the process defined by the function <m>f</m> to the input <m>3t-4</m>, we see that
				<me>
					y = (3t-4)^2 - 1
				</me>,
				which defines <m>y</m> as a function of <m>t</m>.
			</p>

		</solution>
	</example>

	<p>
		When we have a situation such as in <xref ref="ex-composite-introduction">Example</xref> where we use the output of one function as the input of another, we often say that we have <q>composed two functions</q>.  In addition, we use the notation <m>h(t) = f(g(t))</m> to denote that a new function, <m>h</m>, results from composing the two functions <m>f</m> and <m>g</m>.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./previews/PA-changing-composite.xml" />

  </introduction>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-composite-composing">
  	<title>Composing two functions</title>
  	<p>
  		Whenever we have two functions, say <m>g : A \to B</m> and <m>f : B \to C</m>, where the codomain of <m>g</m> matches the domain of <m>f</m>, it is possible to link the two processes together to create a new process that we call the <em>composition</em> of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m>.
  	</p>

  	<definition xml:id="D-composite-compose-functions"> <idx>composite function</idx>
  		<statement>
  			<p>
  				If <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> are functions such that <m>g : A \to B</m> and <m>f : B \to C</m>, we define the <term>composition of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m></term> to be the new function <m>h: A \to C</m> given by 
  				<me>
  					h(t) = f(g(t))
  				</me>.
  				We also sometimes use the notation <m>h = f \circ g</m>, where <m>f \circ g</m> is the single function defined by <m>(f \circ g)(t) = f(g(t))</m>.
  			</p>
  		</statement>
  	</definition>

  	<p>
  		We sometimes call <m>g</m> the <q>inner function</q> and <m>f</m> the <q>outer function</q>.  It is important to note that the inner function is actually the first function that gets applied to a given input, and then then outer function is applied to the output of the inner function.  In addition, in order for a composite function to make sense, we need to ensure that the range of the inner function lies within the domain of the outer function so that the resulting composite function is defined at every possible input.
  	</p>

	  <p>
	    In addition to the possibility that functions are given by formulas,
	    functions can be given by tables or graphs.
	    We can think about composite functions in these settings as well,
	    and the following activities prompt us to consider functions given in this way.
	  </p>

  <xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-composite-tables-graphs.xml" />

  </subsection>
  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-composite-in-context">
  	<title>Composing functions in context</title>
	<p>
		Recall Dolbear's function, <m>T = D(N) = 40 + 0.25N</m>, that relates the number of chirps per minute from a snowy cricket to the Fahrenheit temperature, <m>T</m>.  We earlier established that <m>D</m> has a domain of <m>[40,160]</m> and a corresponding range of <m>[50,85]</m>.  In what follows, we replace <m>T</m> with <m>F</m> to emphasize that temperature is measured in Fahrenheit degrees.
	</p>

	<p>
		The Celcius and Fahrenheit temperature scales are connected by a linear function.  Indeed, the function that converts Fahrenheit to Celcius is
        <me>
        	C = G(F) = \frac{5}{9}(F-32)
        </me>.
        For instance, a Fahrenheit temperature of <m>32</m> degrees corresponds to <m>C = G(32) = 0</m> degrees Celcius.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-composite-crickets-celcius.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-composite-aroc">
  	<title>Function composition and average rate of change</title>

	  <p>
	    Recall that the average rate of change of a function <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[a,b]</m> is given by
	    <me>
	      AV_{[a,b]} = \frac{f(b) - f(a)}{b-a}
	    </me>.
	    In <xref ref="F-composite-aroc-a-b">Figure</xref>, we see the familiar representation of <m>AV_{[a,b]}</m> as the slope of the line joining the points <m>(a,f(a))</m> and <m>(b,f(b))</m> on the graph of <m>f</m>.  In the study of calculus, we progress from the <em>average rate of change on an interval</em> to the <em>instantaneous rate of change of a function at a single value</em>; the core idea that allows us to move from an <em>average</em> rate to an <em>instantaneous</em> one is letting the interval <m>[a,b]</m> shrink in size.
	  </p>

	  <sidebyside width="50%">
	  	<figure xml:id="F-composite-aroc-a-b">
	  		<caption><m>AV_{[a,b]}</m> is the slope of the line joining the points <m>(a,f(a))</m> and <m>(b,f(b))</m> on the graph of <m>f</m>.</caption>
	  		<image source="images/composite-aroc-a-b"/>
	  	</figure>
	  	<figure xml:id="F-composite-aroc-a-h">
	  		<caption><m>AV_{[a,a+h]}</m> is the slope of the line joining the points <m>(a,f(a))</m> and <m>(a,f(a+h))</m> on the graph of <m>f</m>.</caption>
	  		<image source="images/composite-aroc-a-h"/>
	  	</figure>
	  </sidebyside>

	  <p>
	    To think about the interval <m>[a,b]</m> shrinking while <m>a</m> stays fixed, we often change our perspective and think of <m>b</m> as <m>b = a + h</m>, where <m>h</m> measures the horizontal differene from <m>b</m> to <m>a</m>.  This allows us to eventually think about <m>h</m> getting closer and closer to <m>0</m>, and in that context we consider the equivalent expression
	    <me>
	      AV_{[a,a+h]} = \frac{f(a+h) - f(a)}{a+h-a} = \frac{f(a+h) - f(a)}{h} 
	    </me>
	    for the average rate of change of <m>f</m> on	<m>[a,a+h]</m>.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    In this most recent expression for <m>AV_{[a,a+h]}</m>,
	    we see the important role that the composite function
	    <q><m>f(a+h)</m></q> plays.  In particular, to understand the expression for <m>AV_{[a,a+h]}</m> we need to evaluate <m>f</m> at the quantity <m>(a+h)</m>.
	  </p> 

	  <example xml:id="ex-composite-aroc-simplify">
	  	<statement>
	  		<p>
	  			Suppose that <m>f(x) = x^2</m>.  Determine the simplest possible expression you can find for <m>AV_{[3,3+h]}</m>, the average rate of change of <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[3,3+h]</m>.
	  		</p>
	  	</statement>
	  	<solution>
	  		<p>
	  			By definition, we know that 
	  			<me>
	  				AV_{[3,3+h]} = \frac{f(3+h)-f(3)}{h}.
	  			</me>
	  			Using the formula for <m>f</m>, we see that
	  			<me>
	  				AV_{[3,3+h]} = \frac{(3+h)^2-(3)^2}{h}.
	  			</me>
	  			Expanding the numerator and combining like terms, it follows that
				<md>
					<mrow>AV_{[3,3+h]} &amp;= \frac{(9+6h+h^2)-9}{h}</mrow>
					<mrow>   &amp;= \frac{6h + h^2}{h}</mrow>
				</md>.
				Removing a factor of <m>h</m> in the numerator and observing that <m>h \ne 0</m>, we can simplify and find that
				<md>
					<mrow>AV_{[3,3+h]} &amp;= \frac{h(6 + h)}{h}</mrow>
					<mrow>   &amp;= 6+h</mrow>
				</md>.
				Hence, <m>AV_{[3,3+h]} = 6+h</m>, which is the average rate of change of <m>f(x) = x^2</m> on the interval <m>[3,3+h]</m>.<fn>Note that <m>6 + h</m> is a <em>linear</em> function of <m>h</m>.  This computation is connected to the observation we made in <xref ref="T-PA-changing-quadratic-AVs-complete">Table</xref> regarding how there's a linear aspect to how the average rate of change of a quadratic function changes as we modify the interval.</fn>
	  		</p>
	  	</solution>
	  </example> 

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-composite-aroc.xml" />

	<p>
		In <xref ref="act-changing-composite-aroc">Activity</xref>, we see an important setting where algebraic simplification plays a crucial role in calculus.  Because the expresssion 
		<me>
	      AV_{[a,a+h]} = \frac{f(a+h) - f(a)}{h} 
	    </me>
	    always begins with an <m>h</m> in the denominator, in order to precisely understand how this quantity behaves when <m>h</m> gets close to <m>0</m>, a simplified version of this expression is needed.  For instance, as we found in part (b) of <xref ref="act-changing-composite-aroc">Activity</xref>, it's possible to show that for <m>f(x) = 2x^2 - 3x + 1</m>,
	    <me>
	    	AV_{[1,1+h]} = 2h + 1
	    </me>,
	    which is a much simpler expression to investigate.
	</p>

  </subsection>
  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-composite-summary">

  	<title>Summary</title>

  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				When defined, the composition of two functions <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> produces a single new function <m>f \circ g</m> according to the rule <m>(f \circ g)(x) = f(g(x))</m>.  We note that <m>g</m> is applied first to the input <m>x</m>, and then <m>f</m> is applied to the output <m>g(x)</m> that results from <m>g</m>.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				In the composite function <m>h(x) = f(g(x))</m>, the <q>inner</q> function is <m>g</m> and the <m>outer</m> function is <m>f</m>.  Note that the inner function gets applied to <m>x</m> first, even though the outer function appears first when we read from left to right.  The composite function is only defined provided that the codomain of <m>g</m> matches the domain of <m>f</m>: that is, we need any possible outputs of <m>g</m> to be among the allowed inputs for <m>f</m>.  In particular, we can say that if <m>g : A \to B</m> and <m>f : B \to C</m>, then <m>f \circ g : A \to C</m>.  Thus, the domain of the composite function is the domain of the inner function, and the codomain of the composite function is the codomain of the outer function.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Because the expression <m>AV_{[a,a+h]}</m> is defined by
  				<me>
	      			AV_{[a,a+h]} = \frac{f(a+h) - f(a)}{h} 
	    		</me>
	    		and this includes the quantity <m>f(a+h)</m>, the average rate of change of a function on the interval <m>[a,a+h]</m> always involves the evaluation of a composite function expression.  This idea plays a crucial role in the study of calculus.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>

  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-changing-composite.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->
</section>

