<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-circular-traversing">
  <title>Traversing Circles</title>

  <objectives>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How does a point traversing a circle naturally generate a function?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				What are some important properties that characterize a function generated by a point traversing a circle?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How does a circular function change in ways that are different from linear and quadratic functions?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>
  </objectives>

	<introduction>
  		<p>
		    Certain naturally occurring phenomena eventually repeat themselves, especially when the phenomenon is somehow connected to a circle.  For example, suppose that you are taking a ride on a ferris wheel and we consider your height, <m>h</m>, above the ground and how your height changes in tandem with the distance, <m>d</m>, that you have traveled around the wheel.  In <xref ref="F-traversing-ferris-wheel-animation">Figure</xref> we see a snapshot of this situation, which is available as a full animation<fn>Used with permission from Illuminations by the National Council of Teachers of Mathematics. All rights reserved.</fn> at <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/0Dt">http://gvsu.edu/s/0Dt</url>.
  		</p>

  		<figure xml:id="F-traversing-ferris-wheel-animation">
  			<caption>A snapshot of the motion of a cab moving around a ferris wheel.  
			Reprinted with permission from Illuminations by the National Council of Teachers of Mathematics. All rights reserved.</caption>
  			<image width="95%" source="images/traversing-ferris-wheel-animation" />
  		</figure>

  		<p>
  			Because we have two quantities changing in tandem, it is natural to wonder if it is possible to represent one as a function of the other.
  		</p>

  		<xi:include href="./previews/PA-circular-traversing.xml" />

  </introduction>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-traversing-functions">
  	<title>Circular Functions</title> <idx><h>circular functions</h></idx>

	<p>
		The natural phenomenon of a point moving around a circle leads to interesting relationships.  For easier arithmetic, let's consider a point traversing a circle of circumference <m>24</m> and examine how the point's height, <m>h</m>, changes as the distance traversed, <m>d</m>, changes.  Note particularly that each time the point traverses <m>\frac{1}{8}</m> of the circumference of the circle, it travels a distance of <m>24 \cdot \frac{1}{8} = 3</m> units, as seen in <xref ref="F-traversing-first-example">Figure</xref> where each noted point lies <m>3</m> additional units along the circle beyond the preceding one.
	</p>

		<figure xml:id="F-traversing-first-example">
			<caption>A point traversing a circle with circumference <m>C = 24</m>.</caption>
			<image source="images/traversing-first-example" width="45%" />
		</figure>

	<p>
		Note that we know the exact heights of certain points.  Since the circle has circumference <m>C = 24</m>, we know that <m>24 = 2\pi r</m> and therefore <m>r = \frac{12}{\pi} \approx 3.82</m>.  Hence, the point where <m>d = 6</m> (located <m>1/4</m> of the way along the circle) is at a height of <m>h = \frac{12}{\pi} \approx 3.82</m>.  Doubling this value, the point where <m>d = 12</m> has height <m>h = \frac{24}{\pi} \approx 7.64</m>.  Other heights, such as those that correspond to <m>d = 3</m> and <m>d = 15</m> (identified on the figure by the green line segments) are not obvious from the circle's radius, but can be estimated from the grid in <xref ref="F-traversing-first-example">Figure</xref> as <m>h \approx 1.1</m> (for <m>d = 3</m>) and <m>h \approx 6.5</m> (for <m>d = 15</m>).  Using all of these observations along with the symmetry of the circle, we can determine the other entries in <xref ref="T-traversing-first-example-1">Table</xref>.   
	</p>

			<table xml:id="T-traversing-first-example-1">
				<caption>
					Data for height, <m>h</m>, as a function of distance traversed, <m>d</m>.
				</caption>
				<tabular halign="center">
					<row bottom="minor">
					  <cell><m>d</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>0</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>3</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>6</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>9</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>12</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>15</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>18</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>21</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>24</m></cell>
				    </row>
				    <row>
				      <cell><m>h</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>0</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>1.1</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>3.82</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>6.5</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>7.64</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>6.5</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>3.82</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>1.1</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>0</m></cell>
				    </row>				    			    
				</tabular>
			</table>

	<p>
		Moreover, if we now let the point continue traversing the circle, we observe that the <m>d</m>-values will increase accordingly, but the <m>h</m>-values will repeat according to the already-established pattern, resulting in the data in <xref ref="T-traversing-first-example-2">Table</xref>.
	</p>

			<table xml:id="T-traversing-first-example-2">
				<caption>
					Additional data for height, <m>h</m>, as a function of distance traversed, <m>d</m>.
				</caption>
				<tabular halign="center">
					<row bottom="minor">
					  <cell><m>d</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>24</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>27</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>30</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>33</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>36</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>39</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>42</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>45</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>48</m></cell>
				    </row>
				    <row>
				      <cell><m>h</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>0</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>1.1</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>3.82</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>6.5</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>7.64</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>6.5</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>3.82</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>1.1</m></cell>
				      <cell><m>0</m></cell>
				    </row>				    			    
				</tabular>
			</table>	

	<p>
		  It is apparent that each point on the circle corresponds to one and only one height, and thus we can view the height of a point as a function of the distance the point has traversed around the circle, say <m>h = f(d)</m>.  Using the data from the two tables and connecting the points in an intuitive way, we get the graph shown in <xref ref="F-traversing-first-example-graph">Figure</xref>.
	</p>

	<figure xml:id="F-traversing-first-example-graph">
		<caption>The height, <m>h</m>, of a point traversing a circle of radius <m>24</m> as a function of distance, <m>d</m>, traversed around the circle.</caption>
		<image source="images/traversing-first-example-graph" width="80%" />
	</figure>

	<p>
		The function <m>h = f(d)</m> we have been discussing is an example of what we will call a <em>circular function</em>.  <idx><h>circular function</h></idx> Indeed, it is apparent that if we 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					take any circle in the plane,
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					choose a starting location for a point on the circle,
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					let the point traverse the circle continuously,
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					and track the height of the point as it traverses the circle,
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
		the height of the point is a function of distance traversed and the resulting graph will have the same basic shape as the curve shown in <xref ref="F-traversing-first-example-graph">Figure</xref>.  It also turns out that if we track the location of the <m>x</m>-coordinate of the point on the circle, the <m>x</m>-coordinate is also a function of distance traversed and its curve has a similar shape to the graph of the height of the point (the <m>y</m>-coordinate).  Both of these functions are circular functions because they are generated by motion around a circle.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-traversing-2nd-ex.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-traversing-function-properties">
  	<title>Properties of Circular Functions</title>

	<p>
		Every circular function has several important features that are connected to the circle that defines the function.  For the discussion that follows, we focus on circular functions that result from tracking the <m>y</m>-coordinate of a point traversing counterclockwise a circle of radius <m>a</m> centered at the point <m>(k,m)</m>.  Further, we will denote the circumference of the circle by the letter <m>p</m>.
	</p>

		<sidebyside widths="33% 66%">
			<figure xml:id="F-circular-functions-properties-circle">
				<caption>A point traversing the circle.</caption>
				<image source="images/traversing-circular-properties-circle"/>
			</figure>
			<figure xml:id="F-act-circular-functions-properties-graph">
				<caption>Plotting <m>h</m> as a function of <m>d</m>.</caption>
				<image source="images/traversing-circular-properties-graph"/>
			</figure>
		</sidebyside>

	<p>
		We assume that the point traversing the circle starts at <m>P</m> in <xref ref="F-circular-functions-properties-circle">Figure</xref>.  Its height is initially <m>y = m + a</m>, and then its height decreases to <m>y = m</m> as we traverse to <m>Q</m>.  Continuing, the point's height falls to <m>y = m - a</m> at <m>R</m>, and then rises back to <m>y = m</m> at <m>S</m>, and eventually back up to <m>y = m+a</m> at the top of the circle.  If we plot these heights continuously as a function of distance, <m>d</m>, traversed around the circle, we get the curve shown at right in <xref ref="F-act-circular-functions-properties-graph">Figure</xref>.  This curve has several important features for which we introduce important terminology. 
	</p>



	<p>
		The <term>midline</term> <idx><h>circular function</h><h>midline</h></idx> of a circular function is the horizontal line <m>y = m</m> for which half the curve lies above the line and half the curve lies below.  If the circular function results from tracking the <m>y</m>-coordinate of a point traversing a circle, <m>y = m</m> corresponds to the <m>y</m>-coordinate of the center of the circle.  In addition, the <term>amplitude</term> <idx><h>circular function</h><h>amplitude</h></idx> of a circular function is the maximum deviation of the curve from the midline.  Note particularly that the value of the amplitude, <m>a</m>, corresponds to the radius of the circle that generates the curve.
	</p>

	<p>
		Because we can traverse the circle in either direction and for as far as we wish, the domain of any circular function is the set of all real numbers.  From our observations about the midline and amplitude, it follows that the range of a circular function <idx><h>circular function</h><h>range</h></idx> with midline <m>y = m</m> and amplitude <m>a</m> is the interval <m>[m-a,m+a]</m>.
	</p>

	<p>
		Finally, we introduce the formal definition of a <term>periodic</term> function.
	</p>

	<definition>
		<idx><h>function</h><h>periodic</h></idx>
		<idx><h>period</h></idx>
		<statement>
			<p>
				Let <m>f</m> be a function whose domain and codomain are each the set of all real numbers.  We say that <m>f</m> is <term>periodic</term> provided that there exists a real number <m>k</m> such that <m>f(x+k) = f(x)</m> for every possible choice of <m>x</m>.  The smallest value <m>p</m> for which <m>f(x+p) = f(x)</m> for every choice of <m>x</m> is called the <term>period</term> of <m>f</m>.
			</p>
 		</statement>
	</definition>

	<p>
		For a circular function, the period is always the circumference of the circle that generates the curve.  In <xref ref="F-act-circular-functions-properties-graph">Figure</xref>, we see how the curve has completed one full cycle of behavior every <m>p</m> units, regardless of where we start on the curve.
	</p>

	<p>
		Circular functions arise as models for important phenomena in the world around us, such as in a <em>harmonic oscillator</em>. <idx><h>harmonic oscillator</h></idx>  Consider a mass attached to a spring where the mass sits on a frictionless surface.  After setting the mass in motion by stretching or compressing the spring, the mass will oscillate indefinitely back and forth, and its distance from a fixed point on the surface turns out to be given by a circular function.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-traversing-oscillator.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-traversing-aroc">
  	<title>The average rate of change of a circular function</title>
  	<p>
  		Just as there are important trends in the values of a circular function, there are also interesting patterns in the average rate of change of the function.  These patterns are closely tied to the geometry of the circle.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		For the next part of our discussion, we consider a circle of radius <m>1</m> centered at <m>(0,0)</m>, and consider a point that travels a distance <m>d</m> counterclockwise around the circle with its starting point viewed as <m>(1,0)</m>.  We use this circle to generate the circular function <m>h = f(d)</m> that tracks the height of the point at the moment the point has traversed <m>d</m> units around the circle from <m>(1,0)</m>.  Let's consider the average rate of change of <m>f</m> on several intervals that are connected to certain fractions of the circumference.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		Remembering that <m>h</m> is a function of distance traversed along the circle, it follows that the average rate of change of <m>h</m> on any interval of distance between two points <m>P</m> and <m>Q</m> on the circle is given by
  		<me>
  			AV_{[P,Q]} = \frac{\text{change in height}}{\text{distance along the circle}}
  		</me>,
  		where both quantities are measured from point <m>P</m> to point <m>Q</m>.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		First, in <xref ref="F-circular-traversing-aroc-eighth">Figure</xref>, we consider points <m>P</m>, <m>Q</m>, and <m>R</m> where <m>Q</m> results from traversing <m>1/8</m> of the circumference from <m>P</m>, and <m>R</m> <m>1/8</m> of the circumference from <m>Q</m>.  In particular, we note that the distance <m>d_1</m> along the circle from <m>P</m> to <m>Q</m> is the same as the distance <m>d_2</m> along the circle from <m>Q</m> to <m>R</m>, and thus <m>d_1 = d_2</m>.  At the same time, it is apparent from the geometry of the circle that the change in height <m>h_1</m> from <m>P</m> to <m>Q</m> is greater than the change in height <m>h_2</m> from <m>Q</m> to <m>R</m>, so <m>h_1 \gt h_2</m>.  Thus, we can say that
  		<me>
  			AV_{[P,Q]} = \frac{h_1}{d_1} \gt \frac{h_2}{d_2} = AV_{[Q,R]} 
  		</me>.
  	</p>

  	<sidebyside width="50%">
  		<figure xml:id="F-circular-traversing-aroc-eighth">
  			<caption>Comparing the average rate of change over <m>1/8</m> the circumference.</caption>
  			<image source="images/traversing-circular-aroc-circle-eighth" />
  		</figure>
  		<figure xml:id="F-circular-traversing-aroc-20th">
  			<caption>Comparing the average rate of change over <m>1/20</m> the circumference.</caption>
  			<image source="images/traversing-circular-aroc-circle-20th" />
  		</figure>
  	</sidebyside>

  	<p>
  		The differences in certain average rates of change appear to become more extreme if we consider shorter arcs along the circle.  Next we consider traveling <m>1/20</m> of the circumference along the circle.  In <xref ref="F-circular-traversing-aroc-20th">Figure</xref>, points <m>P</m> and <m>Q</m> lie <m>1/20</m> of the circumference apart, as do <m>R</m> and <m>S</m>, so here <m>d_1 = d_5</m>.  In this situation, it is the case that <m>h_1 \gt h_5</m> for the same reasons as above, but we can say even more.  From the green triangle in <xref ref="F-circular-traversing-aroc-20th">Figure</xref>, we see that <m>h_1 \approx d_1</m> (while <m>h_1 \lt d_1</m>), so that <m>AV_{[P,Q]} = \frac{h_1}{d_1} \approx 1</m>.  At the same time, in the magenta triangle in the figure we see that <m>h_5</m> is very small, especially in comparison to <m>d_5</m>, and thus <m>AV_{[R,S]} = \frac{h_5}{d_5} \approx 0</m>.  Hence, in <xref ref="F-circular-traversing-aroc-20th">Figure</xref>,
  		<me>
  			AV_{[P,Q]} \approx 1 \text{ and } AV_{[R,S]} \approx 0
   		</me>.
   		This information tells us that a circular function appears to change most rapidly for points near its midline and to change least rapidly for points near its highest and lowest values.  
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		We can study the average rate of change not only on the circle itself, but also on a graph such as <xref ref="F-act-circular-functions-properties-graph">Figure</xref>, and thus make conclusions about where the function is increasing, decreasing, concave up, and concave down.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-traversing-oscillator-aroc.xml" />
  	</p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-traversing-summary">
  	<title>Summary</title>

  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				When a point traverses a circle, a corresponding function can be generated by tracking the height of the point as it moves around the circle, where height is viewed as a function of distance traveled around the circle.  We call such a function a <em>circular function</em>.  An image that shows how a circular function's graph is generated from the circle can be seen in <xref ref="F-act-circular-functions-properties-graph">Figure</xref>.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Circular functions have several standard features.  The function has a <em>midline</em> that is the line for which half the points on the curve lie above the line and half the points on the curve lie below.  A circular function's <em>amplitude</em> is the maximum deviation of the function value from the midline; the amplitude corresponds to the radius of the circle that generates the function.  Circular functions also repeat themselves, and we call the smallest value of <m>p</m> for which <m>f(x+p) = f(x)</m> for all <m>x</m> the period of the function.  The period of a circular function corresponds to the circumference of the circle that generates the function.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Non-constant linear functions are either always increasing or always decreasing; quadratic functions are either always concave up or always concave down.  Circular functions are sometimes increasing and sometimes decreasing, plus sometimes concave up and sometimes concave down.  These behaviors are closely tied to the geometry of the circle.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>

  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-circular-traversing.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->
</section>

