<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2018                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Preparation for Calculus.                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-changing-linear">
  <title>Linear Functions</title>

  <objectives>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				What behavior of a function makes its graph a straight line?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				For a function whose graph is a straight line, what structure does its formula have?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How can we interpret the slope of a linear function in applied contexts?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction>
  	<p>
  		Functions whose graphs are straight lines are both the simplest and the most important functions in mathematics.
    	Lines often model important phenomena,
    	and even when they don't directly model phenomena,
    	lines can often approximate other functions that do.
    	Whether a function's graph is a straight line or not is connected directly to its average rate of change.
  	</p>

	<xi:include href="./previews/PA-changing-linear-3-ex.xml" />

  </introduction>


  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-linear-properties">
  	<title>Properties of linear functions</title>

	<p>
		In <xref ref="PA-changing-linear-3-ex">Preview Activity</xref>, we considered three different functions for which the average rate of change of each appeared to always be constant.  For the first function in the preview activity, <m>y = f(x) = 7 - 3x</m>, we can compute its average rate of change on an arbitrary interval <m>[a,b]</m>.  Doing so, we notice that
		<md>
			<mrow>AV_{[a,b]} &amp;= \frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</mrow>
			<mrow> 		&amp;= \frac{(7-3b) - (7-3a)}{b-a}</mrow>
			<mrow> 		&amp;= \frac{7-3b - 7+3a}{b-a}</mrow>
			<mrow> 		&amp;= \frac{-3b + 3a}{b-a}</mrow>
			<mrow> 		&amp;= \frac{-3(b - a)}{b-a}</mrow>	
			<mrow> 		&amp;= -3</mrow>		
		</md>.
		This result shows us that for the function <m>y = f(x) = 7 - 3x</m>, its average rate of change is always <m>-3</m>, regardless of the interval we choose.  We will use the property of having constant rate of change as the defining property of a linear function.
	</p>

	<definition xml:id="D-linear-function">
		<idx><h>linear function</h></idx>
		<idx><h>linear function</h><h>slope</h></idx>
		<statement>
			<p>
				A function <m>f</m> is <term>linear</term> provided that its average rate of change is constant on every choice of interval in its domain<fn>Here we are considering functions whose domain is the set of all real numbers.</fn>.  That is, for any inputs <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> for which <m>a \ne b</m>, it follows that 
				<me>
					\frac{f(b) - f(a)}{b-a} = m
				</me>
				for some fixed constant <m>m</m>.  We call <m>m</m> the <term>slope</term> of the linear function <m>f</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</definition>

	<p>
		From prior study, we already know a lot about linear functions.  In this section, we work to understand some familiar properties in light of the new perspective of <xref ref="D-linear-function">Definition</xref>.
	</p>

	<p>
		Let's suppose we know that a function <m>f</m> is linear with average rate of change <m>AV_{[a,b]} = m</m> and that we also know the function value is <m>y_0</m> at some fixed input <m>x_0</m>.  That is, we know that <m>f(x_0) = y_0</m>.  From this information, we can find the formula for <m>y = f(x)</m> for <em>any</em> input <m>x</m>.  Working with the known point <m>(x_0, f(x_0))</m> and any other point <m>(x,f(x))</m> on the function's graph, we know that the average rate of change between these two points must be the constant <m>m</m>.  This tells us that 
		<me>
			\frac{f(x) - f(x_0)}{x-x_0} = m
		</me>.
		Since we are interested in finding a formula for <m>y = f(x)</m>, we solve this most recent equation for <m>f(x)</m>.  Multiplying both sides by <m>(x-x_0)</m>, we see that
		<me>
			f(x) - f(x_0) = m(x-x_0)
		</me>.
		Adding <m>f(x_0)</m> to each side, it follows
		<men xml:id="E-linear-point-slope-first-take">
			f(x) = f(x_0) + m(x-x_0)
		</men>.
		This shows that to determine the formula for a linear function, all we need to know is its average rate of change (or slope) and a single point the function passes through.
	</p>

	<example>
		<statement>
			<p>
				Find a formula for a linear function <m>f</m> whose average rate of change is <m>m = -\frac{1}{4}</m> and passes through the point <m>(-7,-5)</m>.
			</p>

			<p>
				<em>Solution</em>.  Using <xref ref="E-linear-point-slope-first-take">Equation</xref> and the facts that <m>m = -\frac{1}{4}</m> and <m>f(-7) = -5</m> (that is, <m>x_0 = -7</m> and <m>f(x_0) = -5</m>), we have
				<me>
					f(x) = -5 -\frac{1}{4}(x - (-7)) = 5 - \frac{1}{4}(x+7)
				</me>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</example>

	<p>
		Replacing <m>f(x)</m> with <m>y</m> and <m>f(x_0)</m> with <m>y_0</m>, we call <xref ref="E-linear-point-slope-first-take">Equation</xref> the <em>point-slope form</em> <idx>point-slope form</idx> of a line.
	</p>

	<assemblage xml:id="asm-linear-point-slope-form">
		<idx><h>line</h><h>point-slope form</h></idx>
		<title>Point-slope form of a line</title>
		<p>
			A line with slope <m>m</m> (equivalently, average rate of change <m>m</m>) that passes through the point <m>(x_0,y_0)</m> has equation
			<me>
				y = y_0 + m(x-x_0)
			</me>.
		</p>
	</assemblage>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-linear-finding-eqs.xml" />

	<p>
		Visualizing the various components of point-slope form is important.  For a line through <m>(x_0,y_0)</m> with slope <m>m</m>, we know its equation is <m>y = y_0 + m(x-x_0)</m>.  In <xref ref="F-linear-point-slope">Figure</xref>, we see that the line passes through <m>(x_0,y_0)</m> along with an arbitary point <m>(x,y)</m>, which makes the vertical change between the two points given by <m>y - y_0</m> and the horizontal change between the points <m>x - x_0</m>. This is consistent with the fact that
		<me>
			AV_{[x_0,x]} = m = \frac{y-y_0}{x-x_0}
		</me>.
		Indeed, writing <m>m = \frac{y-y_0}{x-x_0}</m> is a rearrangement of the point-slope form of the line, <m>y = y_0 + m(x-x_0)</m>.	
	</p>

	<p>
		We naturally use the terms <q>increasing</q> and <q>decreasing</q> as from <xref ref="D-aroc-increasing-decreasing">Definition</xref> to describe lines based on whether their slope is positive or negative.  A line with positive slope, such as the one in <xref ref="F-linear-point-slope">Figure</xref>, is increasing because its constant rate of change is positive, while a line with negative slope, such as in <xref ref="F-linear-slope-intercept">Figure</xref> is decreasing because of its negative rate of change.  We say that a horizontal line (one whose slope is <m>m = 0</m>) is neither increasing nor decreasing.
	</p>

	<sidebyside width="50%">
		<figure xml:id="F-linear-point-slope">
			<caption>The point-slope form of a line's equation.</caption>
			<image source="images/linear-point-slope" width="50%" />
		</figure>
		<figure xml:id="F-linear-slope-intercept">
			<caption>The slope-intercept form of a line's equation.</caption>
			<image source="images/linear-slope-intercept" width="50%"/>
		</figure>		
	</sidebyside>

	<p>	
		A special case arises when the known point on a line satisfies <m>x_0 = 0</m>.  In this situation, the known point lies on the <m>y</m>-axis, and thus we call the point the <q><m>y</m>-intercept</q> of the line. <idx><h>line</h><h><m>y</m>-intercept</h></idx>  The resulting form of the line's equation is called <em>slope-intercept form</em>, which is also demonstrated in <xref ref="F-linear-slope-intercept">Figure</xref>.
	</p>

	<assemblage xml:id="asm-linear-slope-intercept-form">
		<idx><h>line</h><h>slope-intercept form</h></idx>
		<title>Slope-intercept form</title>
		<p>
			For the line with slope <m>m</m> and passing through <m>(0,y_0)</m>, its equation is 
			<me>
				y = y_0 + mx
			</me>.
		</p>
	</assemblage>

	<p>
		Slope-intercept form follows from point-slope form from the fact that replacing <m>x_0</m> with <m>0</m> gives us <m>y = y_0 + m(x-0) = y_0 + mx</m>.  In many textbooks, the slope-intercept form of a line (often written <m>y = mx + b</m>) is treated as if it is the most useful form of a line.  Point-slope form is actually more important and valuable since we can easily write down the equation of a line as soon as we know its slope and <em>any</em> point that lies on it, as opposed to needing to find the <m>y</m>-intercept, which is needed for slope-intercept form.  Moreover, point-slope form plays a prominent role in calculus.
	</p>

	<p>
		If a line is in slope-intercept or point-slope form, it is useful to be able to quickly interpret key information about the line from the form of its equation.
	</p>

	<example>
		<statement>
			<p>
				For the line given by <m>y = -3 - 2.5(x-5)</m>, determine its slope and a point that lies on the line.
			</p>

			<p>
				<em>Solution</em>.  This line is in point-slope form.  Its slope is <m>m = -2.5</m> and a point on the line is <m>(5,-3)</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</example>

	<example>
		<statement>
			<p>
				For the line given by <m>y = 6 + 0.25x</m>, determine its slope and a point that lies on the line.
			</p>

			<p>
				<em>Solution</em>.  This line is in slope-intercept form.  Its slope is <m>m = 0.25</m> and a point on the line is <m>(0,6)</m>, which is also the line's <m>y</m>-intercept.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</example>

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-linear-context">
  	<title>Interpreting linear functions in context</title>

  	<p>
  		Since linear functions are defined by the property that their average rate of change is constant, linear functions perfectly model quantities that change at a constant rate.  In context, we can often think of slope as a rate of change; analyzing units carefully often yields significant insight.
  	</p>
  	
  	<example xml:id="ex-linear-Dolbear">
  		<statement>
  			<p>
  				The Dolbear function <m>T = D(N) = 40 + 0.25N</m> from <xref ref="sec-changing-functions-models">Section</xref> is a linear function whose slope is <m>m = 0.25</m>.  What is the meaning of the slope in this context?
  			</p>
  		</statement>
  		<solution>
  			<p>
  				Recall that <m>T</m> is measured in degrees Fahrenheit and <m>N</m> in chirps per minute.  We know that <m>m = AV_{[a,b]} = 0.25</m> is the constant average rate of change of <m>D</m>.  Its units are <q>units of output per unit of input</q>, and thus <q>degrees Fahrenheit per chirp per minute</q>.  This tells us that the average rate of change of the temperature function is <m>0.25</m> degrees Fahrenheit per chirp per minute, which means that for each additional chirp per minute observed, we expect the temperature to rise by <m>0.25</m> degrees Fahrenheit.
  			</p>

			<sidebyside width="50%">
				<p>
					Indeed, we can observe this through function values.  We note that <m>T(60) = 55</m> and <m>T(61) = 55.25</m>:  one additional observed chirp per minute corresponds to a <m>0.25</m> degree increase in temperature.  We also see this in the graph of the line, as seen in <xref ref="F-linear-ex-Dolbear-slope">Figure</xref>:
					the slope between the points <m>(40,50)</m> and <m>(120,70)</m> is
	  				<md>
	  					<mrow>m &amp;= \frac{70-50}{120-40}</mrow>
	  					<mrow> &amp;= \frac{20}{80}</mrow>
	  					<mrow> &amp;= 0.25 \frac{\text{degrees F}}{\text{chirp per minute}}</mrow>
	  				</md>.
				</p>
				
				<figure xml:id="F-linear-ex-Dolbear-slope">
  					<caption>The linear Dolbear function with slope <m>m = 0.25</m> degrees Fahrenheit per chirp per minute.</caption>
  					<image width="45%" source="images/linear-Dolbears-Law-slope" />
  				</figure>
			</sidebyside>

  		</solution>
  	</example>	

	<p>
		Like with the Dolbear function, it is often useful to write a linear function (whose output is called <m>y</m>) that models a quantity changing at a constant rate (as a function of some input <m>t</m>) by writing the function relationship in the form
		<me>
			y = b + mt
		</me>
		where <m>b</m> and <m>m</m> are constants.  We may think of the four quantities involved in the following way:
	</p>

	<p>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					The constant <m>b</m> is the <q>starting value</q> of the output that corresponds to an input of <m>t = 0</m>;
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					The constant <m>m</m> is the rate at which the output changes with respect to changes in the input:  for each additional <m>1</m>-unit change in input, the output will change by <m>m</m> units.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					The variable <m>t</m> is the independent (input) variable.  A nonzero value for <m>t</m> corresponds to how much the input variable has changed from an initial value of <m>0</m>.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					The variable <m>y</m> is the dependent (output) variable.  The value of <m>y</m> results from a particular choice of <m>t</m>, and can be thought of as the starting output value (<m>b</m>) plus the change in output that results from the corresponding change in input <m>t</m>.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-linear-Kilimanjaro.xml" />

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-linear-in-context.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-linear-summary">
  	<title>Summary</title>
	  	<ul>
	  		<li>
	  			<p>
	  				Any function <m>f</m> with domain all real numbers that has a constant average rate of change on every interval <m>[a,b]</m> will have a straight line graph.  We call such functions <em>linear</em> functions.
	  			</p>
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			<p>
	  				A linear function <m>y = f(x)</m> can be written in the form <m>y = f(x) = y_0 + m(x-x_0)</m>, where <m>m</m> is the slope of the line and <m>(x_0,y_0)</m> is a point that lies on the line.  In particular, <m>f(x_0) = y_0</m>.
	  			</p>
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			<p>
	  				In an applied context where we have a linear function that models a phenomenon in the world around us, the slope tells us the function's (constant) average rate of change.  The units on the slope, <m>m</m>, are always <q>units of output per unit of input</q> and this enables us to articulate how the output changes in response to a <m>1</m>-unit change in input.
	  			</p>
	  		</li>
	  	</ul>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-changing-linear.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->
</section>

