<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-trig-inverse">
  <title>Inverses of trigonometric functions</title>

  <objectives>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Is it possible for a periodic function that fails the Horizontal Line Test to have an inverse?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				For the restricted cosine, sine, and tangent functions, how do we define the corresponding arccosine, arcsine, and arctangent functions?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				What are the key properties of the arccosine, arcsine, and arctangent functions?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction>
  	  <p>
  		In our prior work with inverse functions, we have seen several important principles, including
	    <ul>
	      <li>
	        <p>
	          A function <m>f</m> has an inverse function
	          if and only if there exists a function <m>g</m> that undoes the work of <m>f</m>:
	          that is, there is some function <m>g</m> for which
	          <m>g(f(x)) = x</m> for each <m>x</m> in the domain of <m>f</m>,
	          and <m>f(g(y)) = y</m> for each <m>y</m> in the range of <m>f</m>.
	          We call <m>g</m> the inverse of <m>f</m>,
	          and write <m>g = f^{-1}</m>.
	        </p>
	      </li>

	      <li>
	        <p>
	          A function <m>f</m> has an inverse function if and only if the graph of <m>f</m> passes the
	          <xref ref="asm-inverse-H-L-test">Horizontal Line Test</xref>.
	        </p>
	      </li>

	      <li>
	        <p>
	          When <m>f</m> has an inverse,
	          we know that writing <q><m>y = f(t)</m></q>
	          and <q><m>t = f^{-1}(y)</m></q>
	          say the exact same thing,
	          but from two different perspectives.
	        </p>
	      </li>
	    </ul>
  	  </p>

	  <p>
	    The trigonometric functions <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m>,
	    <m>g(t) = \cos(t)</m>, and <m>h(t) = \tan(t)</m> are periodic, so each fails the horizontal line test,
	    and thus these functions on their full domains do not have inverse functions.
	    At the same time, it is reasonable to think about changing perspective and viewing angles as outputs in certain restricted settings.
	    For instance, we may want to say both
	    <me>
	      \frac{\sqrt{3}}{2} = \cos\left(\frac{\pi}{6}\right) \ \ \ \ \mbox{and}  \ \ \ \ \frac{\pi}{6} = \cos^{-1}\left(\frac{\sqrt{3}}{2}\right)
	    </me>
	    depending on the context in which we are considering the relationship between the angle and side length.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    It's also important to understand why the issue of finding an angle in terms of a known value of a trigonometric function is important.
	    Suppose we know the following information about a right triangle:
	    one leg has length <m>2.5</m>, and the hypotenuse has length <m>4</m>.
	    If we let <m>\theta</m> be the angle opposite the side of length <m>2.5</m>, it follows that <m>\sin(\theta) = \frac{2.5}{4}</m>.
	    We naturally want to use the inverse of the sine function to solve the most recent equation for <m>\theta</m>.  But the sine function does not have an inverse function, so how can we address this situation?
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    While the original trigonometric functions <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m>,
	    <m>g(t) = \cos(t)</m>, and
	    <m>h(t) = \tan(t)</m> do not have inverse functions,
	    it turns out that we can consider restricted versions of them that do
	    have corresponding inverse functions.  We thus investigate how we can think differently about the 
	    trigonometric functions so that we can discuss inverses in a meaningful way.
	  </p>

	  <xi:include href="./previews/PA-trig-inverse.xml" />

  </introduction>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-trig-inverse-arccos">
  	<title>The arccosine function</title>
  	<p>
  		For the cosine function restricted to the domain <m>[0,\pi]</m> that we considered in <xref ref="PA-trig-inverse">Preview Activity</xref>, the function is strictly decreasing on its domain and thus passes the Horizontal Line Test.  Therefore, this restricted version of the cosine function has an inverse function; we will call this inverse function the <em>arccosine</em> function.
  	</p>

  	<definition xml:id="def-inverse-trig-arccosine">
  		<idx><h>inverse trigonometric functions</h><h>arccosine</h></idx>
  		<statement>
  			<p>
  				Let <m>y = g(t) = \cos(t)</m> be defined on the domain <m>[0,\pi]</m>, and observe <m>g : [0,\pi] \to [-1,1]</m>.  For any real number <m>y</m> that satisfies <m>-1 \le y \le 1</m>, the <term>arccosine of <m>y</m></term>, denoted 
  				<me>
  					\arccos(y)
  				</me>
  				is the angle <m>t</m> satisfying <m>0 \le t \le \pi</m> such that <m>\cos(t) = y</m>.
  			</p>
  		</statement>
  	</definition>

	<p>
		Note particularly that the output of the arccosine function is an angle.  In addition, recall that in the context of the unit circle, an angle measured in radians and the corresponding arc length along the unit circle are numerically equal.  This is why we use the <q>arc</q> in <q>arccosine</q>: given a value <m>-1 \le y \le 1</m>, the arccosine function produces the corresponding <em>arc</em> (measured counterclockwise from <m>(1,0)</m>) such that the cosine of that arc is <m>y</m>.
	</p>

	<p>
		We recall that for any function with an inverse function, the inverse function reverses the process of the original function.  We know that when we write <q><m>y = \cos(t)</m></q>, we can read this statement as saying <q><m>y</m> is the cosine of the angle <m>t</m></q>.  Changing perspective and writing the equivalent statement <q><m>t = \arccos(y)</m></q>, we read this statement as <q><m>t</m> is the angle whose cosine is <m>y</m></q>.  Just as <m>y = f(t)</m> and <m>t = f^{-1}(y)</m> say the same thing for a function and its inverse in general,
		<me>
			y = \cos(t) \text{ and } t = \arccos(y)
		</me>
		say the same thing for any angle <m>t</m> that satisfies <m>0 \le t \le \pi</m>.  We also use the equivalent notation <m>t = \cos^{-1}(y)</m> interchangeably with <m>t = \arccos(y)</m>.  We read <q><m>t = \cos^{-1}(y)</m></q> as <q><m>t</m> is the angle whose cosine is <m>y</m></q> or <q><m>t</m> is the inverse cosine of <m>y</m></q>.  Key properties of the arccosine function can be summarized as follows.
	</p>

	<assemblage xml:id="asm-trig-inverse-arccos-props">
		<title>Properties of the arccosine function</title>
		<sidebyside valign="middle">
			<p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<p>
							The restricted cosine function, <m>y = g(t) = \cos(t)</m>, is defined on the domain <m>[0,\pi]</m> with range <m>[-1,1]</m>.  This function has an inverse function that we call the arccosine function, denoted <m>t = g^{-1}(y) = \arccos(y)</m>.		
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							The domain of <m>y = g^{-1}(t) = \arccos(t)</m> is <m>[-1,1]</m> with range <m>[0,\pi]</m>.
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							The arccosine function is always decreasing on its domain.
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							At right, a plot of the restricted cosine function (in light blue) and its corresponding inverse, the arccosine function (in dark blue).
						</p>
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			
			<image source="images/inverse-trig-arccos-graph" />
			
		</sidebyside>
	</assemblage>

	<p>
		Just as the natural logarithm function allowed us to rewrite exponential equations in an equivalent way (for instance, <m>y = e^t</m> and <m>t = \ln(y)</m> say the exact same thing), the arccosine function allows us to do likewise for certain angles and cosine outputs.  For instance, saying <m>\cos(\frac{\pi}{2}) = 0</m> is the same as writing <m>\frac{\pi}{2} = \arccos(0)</m>, which reads <q><m>\frac{\pi}{2}</m> is the angle whose cosine is <m>0</m></q>.  Indeed, these relationships are reflected in the plot above, where we see that any point <m>(a,b)</m> that lies on the graph of <m>y = \cos(t)</m> corresponds to the point <m>(b,a)</m> that lies on the graph of <m>y = \arccos(t)</m>.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-trig-inverse-arccos.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-trig-inverse-arcsin">
  	<title>The arcsine function</title>
  	<p>
  		We can develop an inverse function for a restricted version of the sine function in a similar way.  As with the cosine function, we need to choose an interval on which the sine function is always increasing or always decreasing in order to have the function pass the horizontal line test.  The standard choice is the domain <m>[-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2}]</m> on which <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m> is increasing and attains all of the values in the range of the sine function.  Thus, we consider <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m> so that <m>f : [-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2}] \to [-1,1]</m> and hence define the corresponding arcsine function.
  	</p>

	<definition  xml:id="def-inverse-trig-arcsine">
  		<idx><h>inverse trigonometric functions</h><h>arcsine</h></idx>
  		<statement>
  			<p>
  				Let <m>y = f(t) = \sin(t)</m> be defined on the domain <m>[-\frac{\pi}{2},\frac{\pi}{2}]</m>, and observe <m>f : [-\frac{\pi}{2},\frac{\pi}{2}] \to [-1,1]</m>.  For any real number <m>y</m> that satisfies <m>-1 \le y \le 1</m>, the <term>arcsine of <m>y</m></term>, denoted 
  				<me>
  					\arcsin(y)
  				</me>
  				is the angle <m>t</m> satisfying <m>-\frac{\pi}{2} \le t \le \frac{\pi}{2}</m> such that <m>\sin(t) = y</m>.
  			</p>
  		</statement>
  	</definition>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-trig-inverse-arcsin.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-trig-inverse-arctan">
  	<title>The arctangent function</title>

  	<p>
  		Finally, we develop an inverse function for a restricted version of the tangent function.  We choose the domain <m>(-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2})</m> on which <m>h(t) = \tan(t)</m> is increasing and attains all of the values in the range of the tangent function.  
  	</p>

	<definition  xml:id="def-inverse-trig-arctan">
  		<idx><h>inverse trigonometric functions</h><h>arctangent</h></idx>
  		<statement>
  			<p>
  				Let <m>y = h(t) = \tan(t)</m> be defined on the domain <m>(-\frac{\pi}{2},\frac{\pi}{2})</m>, and observe <m>h : (-\frac{\pi}{2},\frac{\pi}{2}) \to (-\infty,\infty)</m>.  For any real number <m>y</m>, the <term>arctangent of <m>y</m></term>, denoted 
  				<me>
  					\arctan(y)
  				</me>
  				is the angle <m>t</m> satisfying <m>-\frac{\pi}{2} \lt t \lt \frac{\pi}{2}</m> such that <m>\tan(t) = y</m>.
  			</p>
  		</statement>
  	</definition>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-trig-inverse-arctan.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-trig-inverse-summary">
  	<title>Summary</title>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Any function that fails the Horizontal Line Test cannot have an inverse function.  However, for a periodic function that fails the horizontal line test, if we restrict the domain of the function to an interval that is the length of a single period of the function, we then determine a related function that does, in fact, have an inverse function.  This makes it possible for us to develop the inverse functions of the restricted cosine, sine, and tangent functions.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				We choose to define the restricted cosine, sine, and tangent functions on the respective domains <m>[0,\pi]</m>, <m>[-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2}]</m>, and <m>(-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2})</m>.  On each such interval, the restricted function is strictly decreasing (cosine) or strictly increasing (sine and tangent), and thus has an inverse function.  The restricted sine and cosine functions each have range <m>[-1,1]</m>, while the restricted tangent's range is the set of all real numbers.  We thus define the inverse function of each as follows:
  			</p>

  			<p>
  				<ol label="i.">
  					<li>
  						<p>
  							For any <m>y</m> such that <m>-1 \le y \le 1</m>, the arccosine of <m>y</m> (denoted <m>\arccos(y)</m>) is the angle <m>t</m> in the interval <m>[0,\pi]</m> such that <m>\cos(t) = y</m>.  That is, <m>t</m> is the angle whose cosine is <m>y</m>. 
  						</p>
  					</li>
  					<li>
  						<p>
  							For any <m>y</m> such that <m>-1 \le y \le 1</m>, the arcsine of <m>y</m> (denoted <m>\arcsin(y)</m>) is the angle <m>t</m> in the interval <m>[-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2}]</m> such that <m>\sin(t) = y</m>.  That is, <m>t</m> is the angle whose sine is <m>y</m>. 
  						</p>
  					</li>
  					<li>
  						<p>
  							For any real number <m>y</m>, the arctangent of <m>y</m> (denoted <m>\arctan(y)</m>) is the angle <m>t</m> in the interval <m>(-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2})</m> such that <m>\tan(t) = y</m>.  That is, <m>t</m> is the angle whose tangent is <m>y</m>. 
  						</p>
  					</li>
  				</ol>
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				To discuss the properties of the three inverse trigonometric functions, we plot them on the same axes as their corresponding restricted trigonometric functions.  When we do so, we use <m>t</m> as the input variable for both functions simultaneously so that we can plot them on the same coordinate axes.
  			</p>

          <p>
            The domain of <m>y = g^{-1}(t) = \arccos(t)</m> is <m>[-1,1]</m> with corresponding range <m>[0,\pi]</m>, and the arccosine function is always decreasing.  These facts correspond to the domain and range of the restricted cosine function and the fact that the restricted cosine function is decreasing on <m>[0,\pi]</m>.
          </p>

  			<sidebyside valign="middle">

  				<figure xml:id="F-inverse-trig-arccosine-graph">
  					<caption>The restricted cosine function (in light blue) and its inverse, <m>y = g^{-1}(t) = \arccos(t)</m> (in dark blue).</caption>
  					<image source="images/inverse-trig-arccos-graph" width="50%" />
  				</figure>

          <figure xml:id="F-inverse-trig-arcsine-graph">
            <caption>The restricted sine function (in light blue) and its inverse, <m>y = f^{-1}(t) = \arcsin(t)</m> (in dark blue).</caption>
            <image source="images/inverse-trig-arcsin-graph" width="50%" />
          </figure>

 			</sidebyside>

  				<p>
  					The domain of <m>y = f^{-1}(t) = \arcsin(t)</m> is <m>[-1,1]</m> with corresponding range <m>[-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2}]</m>, and the arcsine function is always increasing.  These facts correspond to the domain and range of the restricted sine function and the fact that the restricted sine function is increasing on <m>[-\frac{\pi}{2},\frac{\pi}{2}]</m>.
  				</p>
  				
  				<p>
  					The domain of <m>y = f^{-1}(t) = \arctan(t)</m> is the set of all real numbers with corresponding range <m>(-\frac{\pi}{2}, \frac{\pi}{2})</m>, and the arctangent function is always increasing.  These facts correspond to the domain and range of the restricted tangent function and the fact that the restricted tangent function is increasing on <m>(-\frac{\pi}{2},\frac{\pi}{2})</m>.
  				</p>

  				<figure xml:id="F-inverse-trig-arctangent-graph">
  					<caption>The restricted tangent function (in light blue) and its inverse, <m>y = h^{-1}(t) = \arctan(t)</m> (in dark blue).</caption>
  					<image source="images/inverse-trig-arctan-graph" width="50%" />
  				</figure>

  		</li>
  	</ul>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-trig-inverse.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->
</section>

