<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-changing-combining">
  <title>Combining Functions</title>

  <objectives>
  		<ul>
  			<li>
  				<p>
  					How can we create new functions by adding, subtracting, multiplying, or dividing given functions? 
  				</p>
  			</li>
  			<li>
  				<p>
  					What are piecewise functions and what are different ways we can represent them?
  				</p>
  			</li>
  		</ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction>

	<p>
		In arithmetic, we execute processes where we take two numbers to generate a new number.  For example, <m>2 + 3 = 5</m>:  the number <m>5</m> results from adding <m>2</m> and <m>3</m>.  Similarly, we can multiply two numbers to generate a new one:  <m>2 \cdot 3 = 6</m>.
	</p>

	<p>
		We can work similarly with functions.  Indeed, we have already seen a sophisticated way to combine two functions to generate a new, related function through composition.  If <m>g : A \to B</m> and <m>f : B \to C</m>, then we know there's a new, related function <m>f \circ g : A \to C</m> defined by the process <m>(f \circ g)(x) = f(g(x))</m>.  Said differently, the new function <m>f \circ g</m> results from executing <m>g</m> first, followed by <m>f</m>. 
	</p>

	<p>
		Just as we can add, subtract, multiply, and divide numbers, we can also add, subtract, multiply, and divide functions to create a new function from two or more given functions.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./previews/PA-changing-combining.xml" />

  </introduction>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-combining-functions-algebra">
  	  <title>Arithmetic with functions</title>
	  <p>
	    In most mathematics up until calculus,
	    the main object we study is <em>numbers</em>.
	    We ask questions such as
	    <ul>
	    	<li>
	    		<p>
	    			<q>what number(s) form solutions to the equation <m>x^2 - 4x - 5 = 0</m>?</q>
	    		</p>
	    	</li>
	    	<li>
	    		<p>
	    			<q>what number is the slope of the line <m>3x - 4y = 7</m>?</q>
	    		</p>
	    	</li>
	    	<li>
	    		<p>
	    			<q>what number is generated as output by the function
	    			<m>f(x) = \sqrt{x^2 + 1}</m> by the input <m>x = -2</m>?</q>
	    		</p>
	    	</li>
	    </ul> 
	    Certainly we also study overall patterns as seen in functions and equations,
	    but this usually occurs through an examination of numbers themselves,
	    and we think of numbers as the main objects being acted upon.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    This changes in calculus.  In calculus, the fundamental objects being studied are
	    functions themselves.  A function is a much more sophisticated mathematical object than a number,
	    in part because a function can be thought of in terms of its graph, which is an infinite collection of ordered pairs of the form <m>(x,f(x))</m>.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	  	It is often helpful to look at a function's formula and observe algebraic structure.  For instance, given the quadratic function
	  	<me>
	  		q(x) = -3x^2 + 5x - 7
	  	</me>
	  	we might benefit from thinking of this as the sum of three simpler functions:  the constant function <m>c(x) = -7</m>, the linear function <m>s(x) = 5x</m> that passes through <m>(0,0)</m> with slope <m>m = 5</m>, and the concave down basic quadratic function <m>w(x) = -3x^2</m>.  Indeed, each of the simpler functions <m>c</m>, <m>s</m>, and <m>w</m> contribute to making <m>q</m> be the function that it is.  Likewise, if we were interested in the function <m>p(x) = (3x^2 + 4)(9 - 2x^2)</m>, it might be natural to think about the two simpler functions <m>f(x) = 3x^2 + 4</m> and <m>g(x) = 9 - 2x^2</m> that are being multiplied to produce <m>p</m>.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	  	We thus naturally arrive at the ideas of adding, subtracting, multiplying, or dividing two or more functions, and hence introduce the following definitions and notation.
	  </p>

	  <definition>
	  	<idx><h>function arithmetic</h><h>sum of</h></idx>
	  	<idx><h>function arithmetic</h><h>difference of</h></idx>	  	
	  	<idx><h>function arithmetic</h><h>product of</h></idx>
	  	<idx><h>function arithmetic</h><h>quotient of</h></idx>
	  	<statement>
	  		<p>
	  			Let <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> be functions that share the same domain.  Then,
		  		<ul>
		  			<li>
		  				<p>
		  					The <term>sum of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m></term> is the function <m>f + g</m> defined by <m>(f+g)(x) = f(x) + g(x)</m>.
		  				</p>
		  			</li>
		  			<li>
		  				<p>
		  					The <term>difference of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m></term> is the function <m>f - g</m> defined by <m>(f-g)(x) = f(x) - g(x)</m>.
		  				</p>
		  			</li>
		  			<li>
		  				<p>
		  					The <term>product of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m></term> is the function <m>f \cdot g</m> defined by <m>(f \cdot g)(x) = f(x) \cdot g(x)</m>.
		  				</p>
		  			</li>
		  			<li>
		  				<p>
		  					The <term>quotient of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m></term> is the function <m>\frac{f}{g}</m> defined by <m>\left( \frac{f}{g} \right)(x) = \frac{f(x)}{g(x)}</m> for all <m>x</m> such that <m>g(x) \ne 0</m>.
		  				</p>
		  			</li>
		  		</ul>
	  		</p>	  			
	  	</statement>
	  </definition>

	  <xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-combining-arithmetic.xml" />

  </subsection>		  

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-combining-functions-context">
  	<title>Combining functions in context</title>
  	<p>
	    When we work in applied settings with functions that model phenomena in the world around us,
	    it is often useful to think carefully about the units of various quantities.
	    Analyzing units can help us both understand the algebraic structure of functions and the variables involved,
	    as well as assist us in assigning meaning to quantities we compute.
	    We have already seen this with the notion of average rate of change:
	    if a function <m>P(t)</m> measures the population in a city in year <m>t</m> and we compute <m>AV_{[5, 11]}</m>,
	    then the units on <m>AV_{[5, 11]}</m> are
	    <q>people per year,</q>
	    and the value of <m>AV_{[5, 11]}</m> is telling us the average rate at which the population changes in people per year on the time interval from year <m>5</m> to year <m>11</m>.
  	</p>

	<example xml:id="ex-combining-stock-value">
		<statement>
			<p>
		      Say that an investor is regularly purchasing stock in a particular company.<fn>This example is taken from <url href="https://activecalculus.org/single/sec-2-3-prod-quot.html">Section 2.3</url> of <url href="https://activecalculus.org/single/">Active Calculus</url>.</fn>
		      Let <m>N(t)</m> represent the number of shares owned on day <m>t</m>,
		      where <m>t = 0</m> represents the first day on which shares were purchased.
		      Let <m>S(t)</m> give the value of one share of the stock on day <m>t</m>;
		      note that the units on <m>S(t)</m> are dollars per share.
		      How is the total value, <m>V(t)</m>, of the held stock on day <m>t</m> determined?
		    </p>

		    <p>
		    	<em>Solution</em>.  Observe that the units on <m>N(t)</m> are <q>shares</q> and the units on <m>S(t)</m> are <q>dollars per share</q>.  Thus when we compute the product
		    	<me>
		        	N(t) \, \text{shares}  \cdot S(t) \, \text{dollars per share}
		      	</me>,
		      	it follows that the resulting units are <q>dollars</q>, which is the total value of held stock.  Hence,
		      	<me>
		      		V(t) = N(t) \cdot S(t)
		      	</me>.
		    </p>
		</statement>
	</example>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-combining-context.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-combining-piecewise">
  	<title>Piecewise functions</title>

  	<p>
  		In both abstract and applied settings,
	    we sometimes have to use different formulas on different intervals in order to define a function of interest.
  	</p>

  	<sidebyside widths="48% 48%" margins="0%">
            <stack>
			<p>
				A familiar and important function that is defined <em>piecewise</em>
			    is the absolute value function: <m>A(x) = |x|</m>.
			    We know that if <m>x \ge 0</m>, <m>|x| = x</m>, whereas if <m>x \lt 0</m>, <m>|x| = -x</m>.  
			</p>
                        <p>
	  		<definition xml:id="def-combining-abs-val">
	  				<idx><h>absolute value function</h></idx>
					<statement>
						<p>
							The absolute value of a real number, denoted by <m>A(x) = |x|</m>, is defined by the rule
			  				<me>
			        			A(x) = 
			        			\begin{cases}
			        				-x, \amp  x \lt  0 \\
			        				x, \amp x \ge 0
			        			\end{cases}
			  				</me>
						</p>
					</statement>
	  		</definition>
                        </p>
            </stack>
  		<figure xml:id="F-combining-defn-abs-val">
  			<caption>A plot of the absolute value function, <m>A(x) = |x|</m>.</caption>
  			<image source="images/combining-piecewise-abs-val" />
  		</figure>
  	</sidebyside>

	<p>
		The absolute value function is one example of a piecewise-defined function.  The <q>bracket</q> notation in <xref ref="def-combining-abs-val">Definition</xref> is how we express which piece of the function applies on which interval.  As we can see in <xref ref="F-combining-defn-abs-val">Figure</xref>, for <m>x</m> values less than <m>0</m>, the function <m>y = -x</m> applies, whereas for <m>x</m> greater than or equal to <m>0</m>, the rule is determined by <m>y = x</m>.
	</p>

	<p>
		As long as we are careful to make sure that each potential input has one and only one corresponding output, we can define a piecewise function using as many different functions on different intervals as we desire.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-changing-combining-piecewise.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-changing-combining-summary">
  	<title>Summary</title>
  	<p>
  		<ul>
  			<li>
  				<p>
  					Just as we can generate a new number by adding, subtracting, multiplying, or dividing two given numbers, we can generate a new function by adding, subtracting, multiplying, or dividing two given functions.  For instance, if we know formulas, graphs, or tables for functions <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> that share the same domain, we can create their product <m>p</m> according to the rule <m>p(x) = (f \cdot g)(x) = f(x) \cdot g(x)</m>. 
  				</p>
  			</li>
  			<li>
  				<p>
  					A piecewise function is a function whose formula consists of at least two different formulas in such a way that which formula applies depends on where the input falls in the domain.  For example, given two functions <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> each defined on all real numbers, we can define a new piecewise function <m>P</m> according to the rule
  					<me>
  						P(x) = 
	        			\begin{cases}
	        				f(x), \amp  x \lt  a \\
	        				g(x), \amp x \ge a
	        			\end{cases}
  					</me>
  					This tells us that for any <m>x</m> to the left of <m>a</m>, we use the rule for <m>f</m>, whereas for any <m>x</m> to the right of or equal to <m>a</m>, we use the rule for <m>g</m>.  We can use as many different functions as we want on different intervals, provided the intervals don't overlap.
  				</p>
  			</li>
  		</ul>
  	</p>
  </subsection>
	
  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-changing-combining.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->
</section>

