<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2018                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Preparation for Calculus.                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-circular-unit-circle">
  <title>The Unit Circle</title>
  <objectives>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				What is the radian measure of an angle?
  			</p>
  		</li>
      <li>
        <p>
          Are there natural special points on the unit circle whose coordinates we can identify exactly?
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          How can we determine arc length and the location of special points in circles other than the unit circle?
        </p>
      </li>
  	</ul>
  </objectives>
  <introduction>
  	<p>
  		As demonstrated by several different examples in <xref ref="sec-circular-traversing">Section</xref>, certain periodic phenomena are closely linked to circles and circular motion.  Rather than regularly work with circles of different center and radius, it turns out to be idal to work with one standard circle and build all circular functions from it.  The <term>unit circle</term> <idx><h>unit circle</h></idx>is the circle of radius <m>1</m> that is centered at the origin, <m>(0,0)</m>.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		If we pick any point <m>(x,y)</m> that lies on the unit circle, the point is associated with a right triangle whose horizontal leg has length <m>|x|</m> and whose vertical leg has length <m>|y|</m>, as seen in <xref ref="F-unit-circle-eqn">Figure</xref>.  By the Pythagorean Theorem, it follows that 
  		<me>
  			x^2 + y^2 = 1
  		</me>,
  		and this is the equation of the unit circle:  a point <m>(x,y)</m> lies on the unit circle if and only if <m>x^2 + y^2 = 1</m>.
  	</p>

	<sidebyside>
		<figure xml:id="F-unit-circle-eqn">
			<caption>Coordinates of a point on the unit circle.</caption>
			<image source="images/unit-circle-eqn" />
		</figure>
		<figure xml:id="F-unit-circle-24s">
			<caption>A point traversing the unit circle.</caption>
			<image source="images/unit-circle-24s" />
		</figure>
	</sidebyside>

	<p>
		To study the circular functions generated by the unit circle, we will also animate a point and let it traverse the circle.  Starting at <m>(1,0)</m> indicated by <m>t_0</m> in <xref ref="F-unit-circle-24s">Figure</xref>, we see a sequence of points that result from traveling a distance along the circle that is <m>1/24</m> the circumference of the unit circle.  Since the unit circle's circumference is <m>C = 2\pi r = 2\pi</m>, it follows that the distance from <m>t_0</m> to <m>t_1</m> is 
		<me>
			d = \frac{1}{24}2\pi = \frac{\pi}{12}
		</me>.
		As we work to better understand the unit circle, we will commonly use fractional multiples of <m>\pi</m> as these result in natural distances traveled along the unit circle.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./previews/PA-circular-unit-circle.xml" />

  </introduction>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-unit-circle-radians-degrees">
    <title>Radians and degrees</title>
    <p>
      In <xref ref="PA-circular-unit-circle">Preview Activity</xref>, we introduced the idea of radian measure of an angle.  Here we state the formal definition of this term.
    </p>

    <definition>
      <idx><h>radian measure</h><h>definition of</h></idx>
      <statement>
        <p>
          An angle whose vertex is at the center of a circle<fn>We often call such an angle a <em>central angle</em>.</fn> measures <term><m>1</m> radian</term> provided that the arc the angle intercepts on the circle equals the radius of the circle.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p>
      As seen in <xref ref="F-PA-unit-circle-defining-radian">Figure</xref>, in the unit circle this means that a central angle has measure <m>1</m> radian whenever it intercepts an arc of length <m>1</m> unit along the circumference.  Because of this important correspondence between the unit circle and radian measure (one unit of arc length on the unit circle corresponds to <m>1</m> radian), we focus our discussion of radian measure within the unit circle. 
    </p>

    <p>
      Since there are <m>2\pi</m> units of length along the unit circle's circumference it follows there are <m>\frac{1}{4} \cdot 2\pi = \frac{\pi}{2}</m> units of length in <m>\frac{1}{4}</m> of a revolution.  We also know that <m>\frac{1}{4}</m> of a revolution corresponds to a central angle that is a right angle, whose familiar degree measure is <m>90^\circ</m>.  If we extend to a central angle that intercepts half the circle, we see similarly that <m>\pi</m> radians corresponds to <m>180^\circ</m>; this relationship enables us to convert angle measures from radians to degrees and vice versa.      
    </p>

    <assemblage>
      <title>Converting between radians and degrees</title>
      <p>
        An angle whose radian measure is <m>1</m> radian has degree measure <m>\frac{180}{\pi} ^\circ</m>.  An angle whose degree measure is <m>1^\circ</m> has radian measure <m>\frac{\pi}{180}</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-unit-circle-radians-degrees.xml" />

    <p>
      Note that in <xref ref="F-PA-big-unit-circle">Figure</xref> in the Preview Activity, we labeled <m>24</m> equally spaced points with their respective distances around the unit circle counterclockwise from <m>(1,0)</m>.  Because these distances are on the unit circle, they also correspond to the radian measure of the central angles that intercept them.  In particular, each central angle with one of its sides on the positive <m>x</m>-axis generates a unique point on the unit circle, and with it, an associated length intercepted along the circumference of the circle.  A good exercise at this point is to return to <xref ref="F-PA-big-unit-circle">Figure</xref> and label each of the noted points with the degree measure that is intercepted by a central angle with one side on the positive <m>x</m>-axis, in addition to the arc lengths (radian measures) already identified.
    </p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-unit-circle-special-points">
    <title>Special points on the unit circle</title>

    <p>
      Our in-depth study of the unit circle is motivated by our desire to better understand the behavior of circular functions.  Recall that as we traverse a circle, the height of the point moving along the circle generates a function that depends on distance traveled along the circle.  Wherever possible, we'd like to be able to identify the exact height of a given point on the unit circle.  Two special right triangles enable us to locate exactly an important collection of points on the unit circle.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-unit-circle-special-triangles.xml" />

    <p>
      Our work in <xref ref="act-circular-unit-circle-special-triangles">Activity</xref> enables us to identify exactly the location of <m>12</m> special points on the unit circle.  In part (d) of the activity, we located the three noted points in <xref ref="F-unit-circle-big-labeled">Figure</xref> along with their respective radian measures.  By symmetry across the coordinate axes and thinking about the signs of coordinates in the other three quadrants, we can now identify all of the coordinates of the remaining <m>9</m> points.  
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-unit-circle-big-labeled">
      <caption>The unit circle with <m>16</m> special points whose location we can determine exactly.</caption>
      <image source="images/unit-circle-16-coords" />
    </figure>

    <p>
      In addition, we note that there are four additional points on the circle that we can locate exactly:  the four points that correspond to angle measures of <m>0</m>, <m>\frac{\pi}{2}</m>, <m>\pi</m>, and <m>\frac{3\pi}{2}</m> radians, which lie where the coordinate axes intersect the circle.  Each such point has <m>0</m> for one coordinate and <m>\pm 1</m> for the other.  Labeling all of the remaining points in <xref ref="F-unit-circle-big-labeled">Figure</xref> is an important exercise that you should do on your own.
    </p>

    <p>
      Finally, we note that we can identify any point on the unit circle exactly simply by choosing one of its coordinates.  Since every point <m>(x,y)</m> on the unit circle satisfies the equation <m>x^2 + y^2 = 1</m>, if we know the value of <m>x</m> or <m>y</m> and the quadrant in which the point lies, we can determine the other coordinate exactly.
    </p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-unit-circle-non-unit-circles">
    <title>Special points and arc length in non-unit circles</title>

    <p>
      All of our work with the unit circle can be extended to circles centered at the origin with different radii, since a circle with a larger or smaller radius is a scaled version of the unit circle.  For instance, if we instead consider a circle of radius <m>7</m>, the coordinates of every point on the unit circle are magnified by a factor of <m>7</m>, so the point that corresponds to an angle such as <m>\theta = \frac{2\pi}{3}</m> has coordinates <m>\left( -\frac{7}{2}, \frac{7\sqrt{3}}{2} \right)</m>.  Distance along the circle is magnified by the same factor:  the arc length along the unit circle from <m>(0,0)</m> to <m>\left( -\frac{7}{2}, \frac{7\sqrt{3}}{2} \right)</m> is <m>7 \cdot \frac{2\pi}{3}</m>, since the arc length along the unit circle for this angle is <m>\frac{2\pi}{3}</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      If we think more generally about a circle of radius <m>r</m> with a central angle <m>\theta</m> that intercepts an arc of length <m>s</m>, we see how the magnification factor <m>r</m> (in comparison to the unit circle) connects arc length and the central angle according to the following principle.
    </p>

    <assemblage>
      <title>Connecting arc length and angles in non-unit circles</title>
      <p>
        If a central angle measuring <m>\theta</m> radians intercepts an arc of length <m>s</m> in a circle of radius <m>r</m>, then
        <me>
          s = r \theta
        </me>.
      </p>

      <p>
        In the unit circle, where <m>r = 1</m>, the equation <m>s = r\theta</m> demonstrates the familiar fact that arc length matches the radian measure of the central angle.  Moreover, we also see how this formula aligns with the definition of radian measure:  if the arc length and radius are equal, then the angle measures <m>1</m> radian.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-unit-circle-non-unit.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          The radian measure of an angle connects the measure of a central angle in a circle to the radius of the circle.  A central angle has radian measure <m>1</m> provided that it intercepts an arc of length equal to the circle's radius.  In the unit circle, a central angle's radian measure is precisely the same numerical value as the length of the arc it intercepts along the circle.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          If we begin at the point <m>(1,0)</m> and move counterclockwise along the unit circle, there are natural special points on the unit circle that correspond to angles of measure <m>30^\circ</m>, <m>45^\circ</m>, <m>60^\circ</m>, and their multiples.  We can count in <m>30^\circ</m> increments and identify special points that correspond to angles of measure <m>30^\circ</m>, <m>60^\circ</m>, <m>90^\circ</m>, <m>120^\circ</m>, and so on; doing likewise with <m>45^\circ</m>, these correspond to angles of <m>45^\circ</m>, <m>90^\circ</m>, <m>135^\circ</m>, etc.  In radian measure, these sequences together give us the important angles <m>\frac{\pi}{6}</m>, <m>\frac{\pi}{4}</m>, <m>\frac{\pi}{3}</m>, <m>\frac{\pi}{2}</m>, <m>\frac{2\pi}{3}</m>, <m>\frac{3\pi}{4}</m>, and on.  Together with our work involving <m>45^\circ</m>-<m>45^\circ</m>-<m>90^\circ</m> and <m>30^\circ</m>-<m>60^\circ</m>-<m>90^\circ</m> triangles in <xref ref="act-circular-unit-circle-special-triangles">Activity</xref>, we are able to identify the exact locations of all of the points in <xref ref="F-unit-circle-big-labeled">Figure</xref>.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          In any circle of radius <m>r</m>, if a central angle of measure <m>\theta</m> radians intercepts an arc of length <m>s</m>, then it follows that 
          <me>
            s = r\theta
          </me>.
          This shows that arc length, <m>s</m>, is magnified along with the size of the radius, <m>r</m>, of the circle.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>

  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-circular-unit-circle.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!--  -->
</section>

