<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2018                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Preparation for Calculus.                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-circular-sine-cosine">
  <title>The Sine and Cosine Functions</title>

  <objectives>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				What are the sine and cosine functions and how do they arise from a point traversing the unit circle?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				What important properties do the sine and cosine functions share?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How do we compute values of <m>\sin(t)</m> and <m>\cos(t)</m>, either exactly or approximately?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction>
  	<p>
  		In <xref ref="sec-circular-traversing">Section</xref>, we saw how tracking the height of a point that is traversing a cirle generates a periodic function, such as in <xref ref="F-act-circular-functions-properties-graph">Figure</xref>.  Then, in <xref ref="sec-circular-unit-circle">Section</xref>, we identified a collection of <m>16</m> special points on the unit circle, as seen in <xref ref="F-circular-sine-all-16">Figure</xref>.
  	</p>

	<figure xml:id="F-circular-sine-all-16">
		<caption>The unit circle with <m>16</m> labeled special points.</caption>
		<image source="images/unit-circle-16-all-labeled" width="80%"/>
	</figure>
  	
	<p>
		You can also use the <em>Desmos</em> file at <url href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/jgddn7tzxg">http://gvsu.edu/s/0xt</url> to review and study the special points on the unit circle.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./previews/PA-circular-sine.xml" />

  </introduction>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-sine-defn">
  	<title>The definition of the sine function</title>
  	<p>
  		The circular function that tracks the height of a point on the unit circle traversing counterclockwise from <m>(1,0)</m> as a function of the corresponding central angle (in radians) is one of the most important functions in mathematics.  As such, we give the function a name:  the <term>sine</term> function.
  	</p>

	<sidebyside widths="50% 50%" valign="middle">

		<p>
			<definition xml:id="def-sine">
				<idx><h>sine function</h></idx>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Given a central angle in the unit circle that measures <m>t</m> radians and that intersects the circle at both <m>(1,0)</m> and <m>(a,b)</m>, as shown in <xref ref="F-def-sine">Figure</xref>, we define the <term>sine of <m>t</m></term>, denoted <m>\sin(t)</m>, by the rule 
						<me>
							\sin(t) = b
						</me>.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</definition>
		</p>

		<figure xml:id="F-def-sine">
			<caption>The definition of the sine of an angle <m>t</m>.</caption>
			<image source="images/sine-defn" />
		</figure>
		
	</sidebyside>

		<p>
			Because of the correspondence between radian angle measure and distance traversed on the unit circle, we can also think of <m>\sin(t)</m> as identifying the <m>y</m>-coordinate of the point after it has traveled <m>t</m> units counterclockwise along the circle from <m>(1,0)</m>.  Note particularly that we can consider the sine of negative inputs:  for instance, <m>\sin(-\frac{\pi}{2}) = -1</m>.
		</p>

	<p>
		Based on our earlier work with the unit circle, we know many different exact values of the sine function, and summarize these in <xref ref="T-circular-sine-values">Table</xref>.
	</p>

  					<table xml:id="T-circular-sine-values">
						<caption>Values of <m>h(t) = \sin(t)</m> at special points on the unit circle.</caption>
						<tabular>
							<row bottom="minor" halign="center">
								<cell><m>t</m></cell>
								<cell><m>0</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{\pi}{6}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{\pi}{4}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{\pi}{3}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{\pi}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{2\pi}{3}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{3\pi}{4}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{5\pi}{6}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\pi</m></cell>		
								<cell><m>\frac{7\pi}{6}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{5\pi}{4}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{4\pi}{3}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{3\pi}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{5\pi}{3}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{7\pi}{4}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{11\pi}{6}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>2\pi</m></cell>						
							</row>
							<row halign="center">
								<cell><m>\sin(t)</m></cell>
								<cell><m>0</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{1}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{\sqrt{3}}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>1</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{\sqrt{3}}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>\frac{1}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>0</m></cell>
								<cell><m>-\frac{1}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>-\frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>-\frac{\sqrt{3}}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>-1</m></cell>
								<cell><m>-\frac{\sqrt{3}}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>-\frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>-\frac{1}{2}</m></cell>
								<cell><m>0</m></cell>
							</row>
						</tabular>
					</table>

	<p>
		Moreover, if we now plot these points in the usual way, as we did in <xref ref="PA-circular-sine">Preview Activity</xref>, we get the familiar circular wave function that comes from tracking the height of a point traversing a circle.  We often call the the graph in <xref ref="F-circular-sine-graph">Figure</xref> the <em>sine wave</em>.
	</p>

  	<figure xml:id="F-circular-sine-graph">
  		<caption>Plot of the sine function on the interval <m>[-\frac{\pi}{4}, \frac{7\pi}{4}]</m>.</caption>
  		<image source="images/sine-definition-graph" />
  	</figure>

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-cosine-defn">
  	<title>The definition of the cosine function</title>
  	<p>
  		Given any central angle of radian measure <m>t</m> in the unit circle with one side passing through the point <m>(1,0)</m>, the angle generates a unique point <m>(a,b)</m> that lies on the circle.  Just as we can view the <m>y</m>-coordinate as a function of <m>t</m>, the <m>x</m>-coordinate is likewise a function of <m>t</m>.  We therefore make the following definition.
  	</p>

	<sidebyside widths="50% 50%" valign="middle">
		<p>
			<definition xml:id="def-cosine">
				<idx><h>cosine function</h></idx>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Given a central angle in the unit circle that measures <m>t</m> radians and that intersects the circle at both <m>(1,0)</m> and <m>(a,b)</m>, as shown in <xref ref="F-def-cosine">Figure</xref>, we define the <term>cosine of <m>t</m></term>, denoted <m>\cos(t)</m>, by the rule 
						<me>
							\cos(t) = a
						</me>.
					</p>
				</statement>
			</definition>
		</p>

		<figure xml:id="F-def-cosine">
			<caption>The definition of the cosine of an angle <m>t</m>.</caption>
			<image source="images/sine-defn-cosine" />
		</figure>
		
	</sidebyside>

	<p>
		Again because of the correspondence between the radian measure of an angle and arc length along the unit circle, we can view the value of <m>\cos(t)</m> as tracking the <m>x</m>-coordinate of a point traversing the unit circle clockwise a distance of <m>t</m> units along the circle from <m>(1,0)</m>.  We now use the data and information we have developed about the unit circle to build a table of values of <m>\cos(t)</m> as well as a graph of the curve it generates.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-sine-cosine.xml" />

  	<p>
  		As we work with the sine and cosine functions, it's always helpful to remember their definitions in terms of the unit circle and the motion of a point traversing the circle.  At <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/0xe">http://gvsu.edu/s/0xe</url> you can explore and investigate a helpful <em>Desmos</em> animation that shows how this motion around the circle generates each of the respective graphs.
  	</p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-sine-cosine-properties">
  	<title>Properties of the sine and cosine functions</title>
  	<p>
  		Because the sine function results from tracking the <m>y</m>-coordinate of a point traversing the unit circle and the cosine function from the <m>x</m>-coordinate, the two functions have several shared properties of circular functions.  
  	</p>


	<assemblage xml:id="asm-sine-cosine-properties">
		<title>
			Properties of the sine and cosine functions
		</title>
		<p>
			For both <m>f(t) = \sin(t)</m> and <m>g(t) = \cos(t)</m>,
		</p>

	  	<p>
	  		<ul>
	  			<li>
	  				<p>
	  					the domain of the function is all real numbers;
	  				</p>
	  			</li>
	  			<li>
	  				<p>
	  					the range of the function is <m>[-1,1]</m>;
	  				</p>
	  			</li>
	  			<li>
	  				<p>
	  					the midline of the function is <m>y = 0</m>;
	  				</p>
	  			</li>
	  			<li>
	  				<p>
	  					the amplitude of the function is <m>a = 1</m>;
	  				</p>
	  			</li>
	  			<li>
	  				<p>
	  					the period of the function is <m>p = 2\pi</m>.
	  				</p>
	  			</li>
	  		</ul>	
	  	</p>		
	</assemblage>

	<p>
		It is also insightful to juxtapose the sine and cosine functions' graphs on the same coordinate axes.  When we do, as seen in <xref ref="F-sine-cosine-both">Figure</xref>, we see that the curves can be viewed as horizontal translations of one another.
	</p>

	<figure xml:id="F-sine-cosine-both">
		<caption>Graphs of the sine and cosine functions.</caption>
		<image source="images/sine-and-cosine-graphs" width="80%" />
	</figure>

	<p>
		In particular, since the sine graph can be viewed as the cosine graph shifted <m>\frac{\pi}{2}</m> units to the right, it follows that for any value of <m>t</m>,
		<me>
			\sin(t) = \cos(t-\frac{\pi}{2})
		</me>.
		Similarly, since the cosine graph can be viewed as the sine graph shifted left,
		<me>
			\cos(t) = \sin(t + \frac{\pi}{2})
		</me>.
		Because each of the two preceding equations hold for every value of <m>t</m>, they are often referred to as <em>identities</em>.
	</p>

	<p>
		In light of the definitions of the sine and cosine functions, we can now view any point <m>(x,y)</m> on the unit circle as being of the form <m>(\cos(t),\sin(t))</m>, where <m>t</m> is the measure of the angle whose vertices are <m>(1,0)</m>, <m>(0,0)</m>, and <m>(x,y)</m>.  Note particularly that since <m>x^2 + y^2 = 1</m>, it is also true that <m>\cos^2(t) + \sin^2(t) = 1</m>.  We call this fact the Fundamental Trigonometric Identity.
	</p>

	<assemblage xml:id="asm-sine-cosine-fund-trid-identity">
		<title>The Fundamental Trigonometric Identity</title>
		<p>
			For any real number <m>t</m>,
			<me>
				\cos^2(t) + \sin^2(t) = 1
			</me>.
		</p>
	</assemblage>

	<p>	
		There are additional trends and patterns in the two functions' graphs that we explore further in the following activity.
	</p>
	
	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-sine-cosine-incr-CCU.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-sine-cosine-computing">
  	<title>Using computing technology</title>
  	<p>
  		We have established that we know the exact value of <m>\sin(t)</m> and <m>\cos(t)</m> for any of the <m>t</m>-values in <xref ref="T-circular-sine-values">Table</xref>, as well as for any such <m>t \pm 2j\pi</m>, where <m>j</m> is a whole number, due to the periodicity of the functions.  But what if we want to know <m>\sin(1.35)</m> or <m>\cos(\frac{\pi}{5})</m> or values for other inputs not in the table?
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		Any standard computing device <dash>a scientific calculator, <em>Desmos</em>, <em>Geogebra</em>, <em>WolframAlpha</em>, etc.</dash> has the ability to evaluate the sine and cosine functions at any input we desire.  Because the input is viewed as an angle, each computing device has the option to consider the angle in radians or degrees.  <em>It is always essential that you are sure which type of input your device is expecting.</em>  Our computational device of choice is <em>Desmos</em>.  In <em>Desmos</em>, you can change the input type between radians and degrees by clicking the wrench icon in the upper right and choosing the desired units.  Radians is the default.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		It take substantial and sophisticated mathematics to enable a computational device to evaluate the sine and cosine functions at any value we want; the algorithms involve an idea from calculus known as an infinite series.  While your computational device is powerful, it's both helpful and important to understand the meaning of these values on the unit circle and to remember the special points for which we know the outputs of the sine and cosine functions exactly.
  	</p>

  	<xi:include href="./activities/act-circular-sine-cosine-computing.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-circular-sine-summary">
  	<title>Summary</title>

  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				The sine and cosine functions result from tracking the <m>y</m>- and <m>x</m>-coordinates of a point traversing the unit circle counterclockwise from <m>(1,0)</m>.  The value of <m>\sin(t)</m> is the <m>y</m>-coordinate of a point that has traversed <m>t</m> units along the circle from <m>(1,0)</m> (or equivalently that corresponds to an angle of <m>t</m> radians), while the value of <m>\cos(t)</m> is the <m>x</m>-coordinate of the same point.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				The sine and cosine functions are both periodic functions that share the same domain (the set of all real numbers), range (the interval <m>[-1,1]</m>), midline (<m>y = 0</m>), amplitude (<m>a = 1</m>), and period (<m>P = 2\pi</m>).  In addition, the sine function is horizontal shift of the cosine function by <m>\frac{\pi}{2}</m> units to the right, so <m>\sin(t) = \cos(t-\frac{\pi}{2})</m> for any value of <m>t</m>.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				If <m>t</m> corresponds to one of the special angles that we know on the unit circle (as in <xref ref="F-circular-sine-all-16">Figure</xref>), we can compute the values of <m>\sin(t)</m> and <m>\cos(t)</m>exactly.  For other values of <m>t</m>, we can use a computational device to estimate the value of either function at a given input; when we do so, we must take care to know whether we are computing in terms of radians or degrees.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>

  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-circular-sine-cosine.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->
</section>

