<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2019                                                        -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Prelude to Calculus.                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-trig-right">
  <title>Right triangles</title>

  <objectives>
  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				How can we view <m>\cos(\theta)</m> and <m>\sin(\theta)</m> as side lengths in right triangles with hypotenuse <m>1</m>?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Why can both <m>\cos(\theta)</m> and <m>\sin(\theta)</m> be thought of as ratios of certain side lengths in any right triangle?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				What is the minimum amount of information we need about a right triangle in order to completely determine all of its sides and angles?
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction>

	<p>
		In <xref ref="sec-circular-sine-cosine">Section</xref>, we defined the cosine and sine functions as the functions that track the location of a point traversing the unit circle counterclockwise from <m>(1,0)</m>.  In particular, for a central angle of radian measure <m>t</m> that passes through the point <m>(1,0)</m>, we define <m>\cos(t)</m> as the <m>x</m>-coordinate of the point where the other side of the angle intersects the unit circle, and <m>\sin(t)</m> as the <m>y</m>-coordinate of that same point, as pictured in <xref ref="F-right-sine-cosine-unit">Figure</xref>.
	</p>

	<p>
		By changing our perspective slightly, we can see that it is equivalent to think of the values of the sine and cosine function as representing the lengths of legs in right triangles.  Specifically, given a central angle<fn>In our work with right triangles, we'll often represent the angle by <m>\theta</m> and think of this angle as fixed, as opposed to our previous use of <m>t</m> where we frequently think of <m>t</m> as changing.</fn> <m>\theta</m>, if we think of the right triangle with vertices <m>(\cos(\theta),0)</m>, <m>(0,0)</m>, and <m>(\cos(\theta), \sin(\theta))</m>, then the length of the horizontal leg is <m>\cos(\theta)</m> and the length of the vertical leg is <m>\sin(\theta)</m>, as seen in <xref ref="F-right-sine-cosine-right">Figure</xref>.  
	</p>

	<sidebyside width="45%">
		<figure xml:id="F-right-sine-cosine-unit">
			<caption>The values of <m>\cos(t)</m> and <m>\sin(t)</m> as coordinates on the unit circle.</caption>
			<image source="images/sine-cosine-unit-circle" width="45%"/>
		</figure>
		<figure xml:id="F-right-sine-cosine-right">
			<caption>The values of <m>\cos(\theta)</m> and <m>\sin(\theta)</m> as the lengths of the legs of a right triangle.</caption>
			<image source="images/sine-cosine-right-triangle" width="45%"/>
		</figure>
	</sidebyside>

	<p>
		This right triangle perspective enables us to use the sine and cosine functions to determine missing information in certain right triangles.  The field of mathematics that studies relationships among the angles and sides of triangles is called <em>trigonometry</em>. <idx><h>trigonometry</h></idx>  In addition, it's important to recall both the Pythagorean Theorem and the Fundamental Trigonometric Identity.  <idx><h>Pythagorean Theorem</h></idx> <idx><h>fundamental trigonometric identity</h></idx>  The former states that in any right triangle with legs of length <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> and hypotenuse of length <m>c</m>, it follows <m>a^2 + b^2 = c^2</m>.  The latter, which is a special case of the Pythagorean Theorem, says that for any angle <m>\theta</m>, <m>\cos^2(\theta) + \sin^2(\theta) = 1</m>.
	</p>

  	<xi:include href="./previews/PA-trig-right.xml" />

  </introduction>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-trig-right-similar">
  	<title>The geometry of triangles</title>

  	<p>
  		In the study of functions, linear functions are the simplest of all and form a foundation for our understanding of functions that have other shapes.  In the study of geometric shapes (polygons, circles, and more), the simplest figure of all is the triangle, and understanding triangles is foundational to understanding many other geometric ideas.  To begin, we list some familiar and important facts about triangles.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		<ul>
  			<li>
  				<p>
  					Any triangle has <m>6</m> important features:  <m>3</m> sides and <m>3</m> angles.
  				</p>
  			</li>
  			<li>
  				<p>
  					In any triangle in the Cartesian plane, the sum of the measures of the interior angles is <m>\pi</m> radians (or equivalently, <m>180^\circ</m>).
  				</p>
  			</li>
  			<li>
  				<p>
  					In any triangle in the plane, knowing three of the six features of a triangle is often enough information to determine the missing three features.<fn>Formally, this idea relies on what are called <em>congruence criteria</em>.  For instance, if we know the lengths of all three sides, then the angle measures of the triangle are uniquely determined.  This is called the Side-Side-Side Criterion (SSS).  You are likely familiar with SSS, as well as SAS (Side-Angle-Side), ASA, and AAS, which are the four standard criteria.</fn>
  				</p>
  			</li>
  		</ul>
  	</p>

	<p>
		The situation is especially nice for right triangles, because then we only have five unknown features since one of the angles is <m>\frac{\pi}{2}</m> radians (or <m>90^\circ</m>), as demonstrated in <xref ref="F-right-triangle-5">Figure</xref>.  If we know one of the two non-right angles,
		then we know the other as well.  Moreover, if we know any two sides, we can immediately deduce the third, because of the Pythagorean Theorem.  As we saw in <xref ref="PA-trig-right">Preview Activity</xref>, the cosine and sine functions offer additional help in determining missing information in right triangles.  Indeed, while the functions <m>\cos(t)</m> and <m>\sin(t)</m> have many important applications in modeling periodic phenomena such as osciallating masses on springs, they also find powerful application in settings involving right triangles, such as in navigation and surveying.
	</p>

		<figure xml:id="F-right-triangle-5">
			<caption>The <m>5</m> potential unknowns in a right triangle.</caption>
			<image source="images/right-triangle-5" width="70%"/>
		</figure>

	<p>
		Because we know the values of the cosine and sine functions from the unit circle, right triangles with hypotentuse <m>1</m> are the easiest ones in which to determine missing information.  In addition, we can relate any other right triangle to a right triangle with hypotenuse <m>1</m> through the concept of <em>similarity</em>.  Recall that two triangles are <term>similar</term> <idx><h>similar triangles</h></idx> provided that one is a magnification of the other.  More precisely, two triangles are similar whenever there is some constant <m>k</m> such that every side in one triangle is <m>k</m> times as long as the corresponding side in the other and the corresponding angles in the two triangles are equal.  An important result from geometry tells us that if two triangles are known to have all three of their corresponding angles equal, then it follows that the two triangles are similar, and therefore their corresponding sides must be proportionate to one another.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-trig-right-similar.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-trig-right-ratios">
  	<title>Ratios of sides in right triangles</title>

  	<p>
  		A right triangle with a hypotenuse of length <m>1</m> can be viewed as lying in standard position in the unit circle, with one vertex at the origin and one leg along the positive <m>x</m>-axis.  If we let the angle formed by the hypotenuse and the horizontal leg have measure <m>\theta</m>, then the right triangle with hypotenuse <m>1</m> has horizontal leg of length <m>\cos(\theta)</m> and vertical leg of length <m>\sin(\theta)</m>.  If we now consider a similar right triangle with hypotenuse of length <m>r \ne 1</m>, we can view that triangle as a magnification of a triangle with hypotenuse <m>1</m>.  These observations, combined with our work in <xref ref="act-trig-right-similar">Activity</xref>, show us that the horizontal legs of the right triangle with hypotenuse <m>r</m> have measure <m>r\cos(\theta)</m> and <m>r\sin(\theta)</m>, as pictured in <xref ref="F-right-triangle-r-theta">Figure</xref>.
  	</p>

		<figure xml:id="F-right-triangle-r-theta">
			<caption>The roles of <m>r</m> and <m>\theta</m> in a right triangle.</caption>
			<image width="70%" source="images/right-triangle-r-theta"/>
		</figure>

	<p>
		From the similar triangles in <xref ref="F-right-triangle-r-theta">Figure</xref>, we can make an important observation about ratios in right triangles.  Because the triangles are similar, the ratios of corresponding sides must be equal, so if we consider the two hypotenuses and the two horizontal legs, we have
		<men xml:id="eq-right-COH">
			\frac{r}{1} = \frac{r\cos(\theta)}{\cos(\theta)}
		</men>.
		If we rearrange <xref ref="eq-right-COH">Equation</xref> by dividing both sides by <m>r</m> and multiplying both sides by <m>\cos(\theta)</m>, we see that
		<men xml:id="eq-right-COH-2">
			\frac{\cos(\theta)}{1} = \frac{r\cos(\theta)}{r}
		</men>.
		From a geometric perspective, <xref ref="eq-right-COH-2">Equation</xref> tells us that the ratio of the horizontal leg of a right triangle to the hypotenuse of the triangle is always the same (regardless of <m>r</m>) and that the value of that ratio is <m>\cos(\theta)</m>, where <m>\theta</m> is the angle adjacent to the horizontal leg.  In an analogous way, the equation involving the hypotenuses and vertical legs of the similar triangles is
		<men xml:id="eq-right-SOH">
			\frac{r}{1} = \frac{r\sin(\theta)}{\sin(\theta)}
		</men>,
		which can be rearranged to
		<men xml:id="eq-right-SOH-2">
			\frac{\sin(\theta)}{1} = \frac{r\sin(\theta)}{r}
		</men>.
		<xref ref="eq-right-SOH-2">Equation</xref> shows that the ratio of the vertical leg of a right triangle to the hypotenuse of the triangle is always the same (regardless of <m>r</m>) and that the value of that ratio is <m>\sin(\theta)</m>, where <m>\theta</m> is the angle opposite the vertical leg.  We summarize these recent observations as follows.
	</p>

	<assemblage xml:id="asm-trig-right-SOH-CAH">
		<title>Ratios in right triangles</title>
			<sidebyside widths="60% 40%">
				<p>
					In a right triangle where one of the non-right angles is <m>\theta</m>, and <q>adj</q> denotes the length of the leg adjacent to <m>\theta</m>, <q>opp</q> the length the side opposite <m>\theta</m>, and <q>hyp</q> the length of the hypotenuse,
					<me>
						\cos(\theta) = \frac{\text{adj}}{\text{hyp}} \text{ and } \sin(\theta) = \frac{\text{opp}}{\text{hyp}}
					</me>.
				</p>

				<image source="images/right-triangle-SOH-CAH" width="50%" />

			</sidebyside>
	</assemblage>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-trig-right-SOH-CAH.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-trig-right-ratios-sin-cos">
  	<title>Using a ratio involving sine and cosine</title>

  	<p>
  		In <xref ref="act-trig-right-SOH-CAH">Activity</xref>, we found that in many cases where we have a right triangle, knowing two additional pieces of information enables us to find the remaining three unknown quantities in the triangle.  At this point in our studies, the following general principles hold.  
	</p>

	<assemblage xml:id="asm-trig-right-missing-info">
		<title>Missing information in right triangles</title>
			<p>
					In any right triangle,
			</p>

			<p>
		  		<ol>
		  			<li>
		  				<p>
		  					if we know one of the non-right angles and the length of the hypotenuse, we can find both the remaining non-right angle and the lengths of the two legs;
		  				</p>
		  			</li>
		  			<li>
		  				<p>
		  					if we know the length of two sides of the triangle, then we can find the length of the other side;
		  				</p>
		  			</li>
		  			<li>
		  				<p>
		  					if we know the measure of one non-right angle, then we can find the measure of the remaining angle.
		  				</p>
		  			</li>
		  		</ol>
			</p>
	</assemblage>

  	<p>
  		In scenario (1.), all <m>6</m> features of the triangle are not only determined, but we are able to find their values.  In (2.), the triangle is uniquely determined by the given information, but as in <xref ref="act-trig-right-SOH-CAH">Activity</xref> parts (d) and (e), while we know the values of the sine and cosine of the angles in the triangle, we haven't yet developed a way to determine the measures of those angles.  Finally, in scenario (3.), the triangle is not uniquely determined, since any magnified version of the triangle will have the same three angles as the given one, and thus we need more information to determine side length.
  	</p>

  	<p>
  		We will revisit scenario (2) in our future work.  Now, however, we want to consider a situation that is similar to (1), but where it is one leg of the triangle instead of the hypotenuse that is known.  We encountered this in <xref ref="act-trig-right-SOH-CAH">Activity</xref> part (f): a right triangle where one of the non-right angles is <m>\beta = \frac{\pi}{5}</m> and the leg opposite this angle has length <m>4</m>.
  	</p>

	<example xml:id="ex-right-sin-cos-ratio">  
		<statement>

		<sidebyside widths="55% 40%" margins="0% 0%">
                    <stack>
		    <p>
					Consider a right triangle in which one of the non-right angles is <m>\beta = \frac{\pi}{5}</m> and the leg opposite <m>\beta</m> has length <m>4</m>.  
				</p>

				<p>
					Determine (both exactly and approximately) the measures of all of the remaining sides and angles in the triangle.
				</p>
			</stack>

				<figure xml:id="F-right-triangle-ex-ratio">
					<caption>The given right triangle.</caption>
					<image source="images/right-triangle-ex-ratio" width="35%"/>
				</figure>
		</sidebyside>
			

		</statement>
		<solution>
				<p>
					From the fact that <m>\beta = \frac{\pi}{5}</m>, it follows that <m>\alpha = \frac{\pi}{2} - \frac{\pi}{5} = \frac{3\pi}{10}</m>.  In addition, we know that
					<men xml:id="eq-right-sin-ratio">
						\sin\left(\frac{\pi}{5}\right) = \frac{4}{h}
					</men>
					and
					<men xml:id="eq-right-cos-ratio">
						\cos\left(\frac{\pi}{5}\right) = \frac{x}{h}
					</men>
				</p>

			<p>
				Solving <xref ref="eq-right-sin-ratio">Equation</xref> for <m>h</m>, we see that
				<men xml:id="eq-right-sin-ratio-2">
						h = \frac{4}{\sin\left(\frac{\pi}{5}\right)}
				</men>, which is the exact numerical value of <m>h</m>.  Substituting this result in 
				<xref ref="eq-right-cos-ratio">Equation</xref>, we find that
				<men xml:id="eq-right-cos-ratio-2">
						\cos\left(\frac{\pi}{5}\right) = \frac{x}{\frac{4}{\sin\left(\frac{\pi}{5}\right)}}
				</men>.
				Solving this equation for the single unknown <m>x</m> shows that
				<me>
					x = \frac{4 \cos\left(\frac{\pi}{5}\right)}{\sin\left(\frac{\pi}{5}\right)}
				</me>.
				The approximate values of <m>x</m> and <m>h</m> are <m>x \approx 5.506</m> and <m>h \approx  6.805</m>.
			</p>
		</solution>
	</example>

	<p>
		<xref ref="ex-right-sin-cos-ratio">Example</xref> demonstrates that a ratio of values of the sine and cosine function can be needed in order to determine the value of one of the missing sides of a right triangle, and also that we may need to work with two unknown quantities simultaneously in order to determine both of their values.
	</p>

	<xi:include href="./activities/act-trig-right-sine-cosine-ratio.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
  	<title>Summary</title>

  	<ul>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				In a right triangle with hypotenuse <m>1</m>, we can view <m>\cos(\theta)</m> as the length of the leg adjacent to <m>\theta</m> and <m>\sin(\theta)</m> as the length of the leg opposite <m>\theta</m>, as seen in <xref ref="F-right-sine-cosine-right">Figure</xref>.  This is simply a change in perspective achieved by focusing on the triangle as opposed to the unit circle.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Because a right triangle with hypotenuse of length <m>r</m> can be thought of as a scaled version of a right triangle with hypotenuse of length <m>1</m>, we can conclude that in a right triangle with hypotenuse of length <m>r</m>, the leg adjacent to angle <m>\theta</m> has length <m>r\cos(\theta)</m>, and the leg opposite <m>\theta</m> has length <m>r\sin(\theta)</m>, as seen in <xref ref="F-right-triangle-r-theta">Figure</xref>.  Moreover, in any right triangle with angle <m>\theta</m>, we know that
  				<me>
					\cos(\theta) = \frac{\text{adj}}{\text{hyp}} \text{ and } \sin(\theta) = \frac{\text{opp}}{\text{hyp}}
				</me>.
			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				In a right triangle, there are five additional characteristics:  the measures of the two non-right angles and the lengths of the three sides.  In general, if we know one of those two angles and one of the three sides, we can determine all of the remaining pieces.
  			</p>
  		</li>
  	</ul>

  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-trig-right.xml" />

  <!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->
</section>

